<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The declaration of the Commission of the General Assembly, to this whole Kirk and kingdom of Scotland of the fifth of May: concerning the present publike proceedings towards an engagement in warre, so farre as religion is therein concerned. Together with their desires and petitions to the Honourable Court of Parliament, the Parliaments answers. Their humble returnes and representations, and other papers that may give full and cleare information in the matter.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 176 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79719</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4216A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E461_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29223</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872226</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872226</idno>
            <idno type="VID">124652</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79719)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 124652)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 73:E461[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The declaration of the Commission of the General Assembly, to this whole Kirk and kingdom of Scotland of the fifth of May: concerning the present publike proceedings towards an engagement in warre, so farre as religion is therein concerned. Together with their desires and petitions to the Honourable Court of Parliament, the Parliaments answers. Their humble returnes and representations, and other papers that may give full and cleare information in the matter.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>56, 51-62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T.R. and E.M.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug ye 26".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in Harvard Library (Early English books), and the British Library (Thomason Tracts).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Foreign relations --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:124652:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DECLARATION Of the Commiſſion of the <hi>GENERAL ASSEMBLY,</hi> To this whole Kirk and Kingdom of SCOTLAND Of the fifth of <hi>May:</hi> Concerning the preſent publike proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings towards an engagement in Warre, ſo farre as Religion is therein concerned.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER With their Deſires and Petitions to the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Court of Parliament, The Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments Anſwers.</p>
            <p>Their humble Returnes and Repreſentations, and other Papers that may give full and cleare information in the matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>T.R.</hi> and <hi>E. M.</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:124652:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:124652:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A DECLARATION</hi> Of the COMMISSION of the GENERALL ASSEMBLY, to this whole Kirk and Kingdome, concerning the preſent publike proceedings towards an engagement in Warre, ſo farre as Religion is therein concerned.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD onely wiſe, who is <hi>wonderfull in counſel and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in working,</hi> whoſe thoughts are not like mens thoughts, nor his wayes like mens wayes; Who ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by weak and unlikely meanes, and often by contrary meanes, uſeth to work out the greateſt works of his glory, and the greateſt ſalvation to his people: After he had broken the Egyptian Antichriſtian yoke, firſt in this, then in the neighbour-Kingdome, <hi>with a mighty hand and a ſtretched out arm;</hi> and had alſo brought us through a red Sea of a bloody oppoſition and Warre; yea, after we were near the wiſhed for Reformation and Peace, He hath againe reduced us to ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme difficulties and dangers, as makes many in their haſte apt to wiſh they had not come out of Egypt, or that they were returned thither againe. How great and how many ſoever our dangers be, <hi>The Lord is righteous in all his wayes, and holy in all his Works,</hi> and he hath <hi>puniſhed us leſſe then our iniquities deſerve.</hi> Among many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther provocations, that of Sinfull compliance is one, which the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent judgments of God in both Kingdomes do more eſpecially and more diſtinctly proclaime and ſpeak out (Eccho-wiſe) unto us. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries</hi> in the one hand, and <hi>Malignants</hi> in both, were ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nived at and complied with, that God hath moſt juſtly made them on both ſides to be thorns and ſcourges to theſe that cheriſhed them when they ſhould have ſuppreſſed them. But as we will <hi>beare the indignation of the Lord, becauſe we have ſinned againſt him:</hi> So we
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:124652:3"/>encourage our ſelves in our God and truſt, that when he hat hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and proved his people, he will do them good in their latter end. Bleſſed are they that wait for him, and live by faith, and keep their garments clean, for they ſhall <hi>ſee the good of Jeruſalem, and peace upon Iſrael.</hi> yea, God ſhall work ſo much good out of all the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt evils which now afflict them, that they ſhall ſay in end, We had periſhed, unleſſe we had periſhed; and the work of God had not been done, if it had not been undone.</p>
            <p>It is one door of hope to us, that God hath raiſed up the ſpirits of many of his ſervants in divers places and Provinces of <hi>England,</hi> to joyne together in witneſſing a good confeſſion, and giving a fair publike teſtimony for the truth of Chriſt, for the Covenant, for the Presbyterial Government, and againſt that abominable Toleration of moſt dangerous Errors. Hereſies and Schiſmes. Theſe <hi>Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> we have ſeen to our great joy and comfort, and have beene much refreſhed thereby; truſting, that ſo many publike Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies as have been given in both Kingdomes for the Covenant, and againſt the Toleration of Hereſie or Schiſme, ſhall not be in vaine, but that God ſhall lay open thoſe that reſiſt the truth, ſo as <hi>they ſhall proceed no further, but their folly ſhall be made manifeſt unto all men.</hi> And we not doubt, but that ſuch ſhoutings ſhall be heard among the Churches of Chriſt: Shame, ſhame upon the way of the Sectaries! Grace, grace upon that Covenant and Reformation which the Sectaries oppoſed!</p>
            <p>Our preſent-work is at home, To give an Antidote againſt theſe Malignant deſignes now brought to ſo much maturity: and withall to clear our owne late Proceedings, which ſome are content to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtand, except they alſo miſrepreſent them to as many others as they can; yea ſome are ſo skilful in coyning, others ſo bold in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and a third ſort ſo weak and ſimple in believing lies and calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, that euery conſcientious man hath cauſe to pray at this time, <hi>Deliver my ſoul, O Lord, from lying lips and from a deceitfull tongue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That we may therefore lay more open the truth of matters, we ſhall not now ſo farre runne the back-trade as to insist upon the riſe and progreſſe of theſe preſent evils, nor upon the grounds of our former feares and apprehenſions of dangerous and malignant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes heretofore on foot: It ſhall be ſufficient at this time to make known the late paſſages, ſince we received His Majeſties <hi>Letter</hi> da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:124652:3"/>at <hi>Carisbrook</hi> Caſtle, <hi>December</hi> 27. 1647. together with a Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative in writing of his Majeſties conceſſions and offers concerning Religion, and what his Majeſtie is content to do for this Kingdome <hi>(upon a good agreement)</hi> under which expreſſion we know not how much may be comprehended. That Letter and Narrative, together with the reports which then this Kingdome was full of, that his Majeſty had given ſatisfaction to the publike deſires concerning the Covenant and Religion (thereby to make the people ſecure, and the better to animate them unto an engagement in his Majeſties quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel) did miniſter occaſion to our late <hi>Declaration,</hi> which although extremely oppoſed and maligned by ſuch as found their projects thereby croſſed, yet hath found ſuch generall and good acceptance in this Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that we have already received not onely from divers Presbyteries, but from the moſt part of the Provinciall Synods, moſt affectionate Letters of thanks for the ſame; as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the Provinciall of <hi>Lothian</hi> and <hi>Tweddale, Eyffe, Menſe,</hi> and <hi>Tiviotdail, Perth</hi> and <hi>Stirlin, Angus</hi> and <hi>Mernes, Glaſgow</hi> and <hi>Air, Dumfreis, Galloway,</hi> and <hi>Aberdeen:</hi> And we doubt not but that the few other Provincials would have done the like, but that being in more remote places, they had not the opportunity to be ſo ſoon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the condition of publike affairs.</p>
            <p>Not long after the emitting of that Declaration, we were deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, upon the 15 of <hi>March,</hi> by the Committee of Parliament to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point ſome of our number to conferre with their Lordſhips, which we did: But upon the 17. of that moneth, underſtanding that a Vote had paſt in Parliament upon the 16. concerning <hi>Berwick</hi> and <hi>Carlile,</hi> (which Vote as it was diſſented from and proteſted againſt by divers Members of Parliament who have beene moſt zealous and conſtant ſince the beginning, ſo we conceived to be a predeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining of the ſubject of the Conference, and to be of exceeding dangerous conſequence to the cauſe of God and ends of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant) We were thereupon diſcouraged from entertaining that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, and ſo reſolved to delay it till we ſhould give further Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to thoſe of our Number appointed on the Conference.</p>
            <p>After this, upon the 22. of <hi>March,</hi> we did, for our owne exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and for a cleare underſtanding between the Honourable Court of Parliament and us, repreſent to their Lordſhips, eight hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſires, whereupon the ſame day we were invited to a new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with ſome of their Lordſhips which did not produce the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:124652:4"/>wiſhed effect and ſatisfaction which we were waiting for. Upon the 28. of <hi>March</hi> we received the Parliaments anſwers to our eight De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, which leaving us ſtill unſatisfied, did occaſion our humble Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of <hi>March</hi> 29. whereunto we received no other anſwer, but a deſire of Parliament ſent us the next day, for a conference up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſaid Deſires, and the parliaments anſwer thereunto, and alſo upon the ſtate of the Queſtion and whole matter. But as we were willing to conferre upon our 8 deſires, and the unſatisfactorineſſe of the parliaments anſwers thereunto, ſo till we ſhould receive a cleer and reall ſatisfaction to theſe our deſires, we Declined a Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence upon the ſtate of a Queſtion for Warre, for the Grounds and reaſons expreſſed in our paper of the 30 of <hi>March,</hi> and did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly give order to thoſe of our number appointed to conferre. But the power given to the Committee of Parliament, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing of further ſatisfaction to be give to our deſires, that their Conference (after ſome time ſpent in debates) proved no leſſe ineffectuall then the former two.</p>
            <p>Upon the 11 <hi>April.</hi> It was Ordered by the Parliament, that the demand concerning Religion, thought fit by their Lordſhips to be ſent to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould be communicated unto us: whereunto we returned an anſwer by our Paper of the 13. of that moneth. And that we might leave no meanes uneſſayed for ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in thoſe particulars, (wherein moſt part of the Provincial Synods hath joyned with us in ſupplications to the Parliament) without which, many others, as well as our ſelves, could not be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in conſcience to concurre in the Engagement) We did by our Petition of the 18. further inſiſt with their Lordſhips in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and earneſtneſſe for ſatisfaction to our deſires, and to be clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon the whole matter. Unto all which we have received no other anſwers for the ſatisfaction of our conſciences, but the Paper delivered in to us from the Parliament upon the 20. of <hi>April,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their Lordſhips <hi>Declaration,</hi> unto which we were remitted for ſatisfaction in moſt things we had deſired, But how great reaſon we have to be ſtill unſatisfied, will appeare by our Anſwer to their Lordſhips paper of the 20. of <hi>April,</hi> and by our humble <hi>Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> upon the <hi>Declaration</hi> it ſelfe, expreſſing more fully our ſenſe of the whole matter: and although we might have juſtly deſired ſome weeks for deliberation about an Anſwer to ſo large and ſo premedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate a Declaration concerning things of ſo high a nature, yet we
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:124652:4"/>made much haſte, that our <hi>Repreſentation</hi> thereupon was fully agreed and concluded among us upon the eight day after we received the <hi>Declaration</hi> it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>If the Honourable Eſtates of Parliament had been pleaſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay the ſending away of their demands to <hi>England,</hi> and the publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>Declaration</hi> to this Kingdom, till they had received and conſidered our Humble <hi>Repreſentation</hi> thereupon, We know not but it might have, by the bleſſing of God, conduced much to the preventing of great and ſad inconveniences. But now their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips <hi>Declaration</hi> being emitted as it is, we have too much cauſe to feare, that the Malignant party ſhall make uſe of it to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnaring of many, unleſſe timous warning and information be given them. For our part, it hath been our endeavour (which we are confident is deſired with us by all the well-affected both in Church and State) that there may be no rupture in this Nation, but a firme union and conjunction upon the firſt principles and grounds of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging in this cauſe. And as we have not been tenacious of words, but of things, nor of any other things but ſuch as highly concerne the glory of God, ſolemn Covenants, and the good, ſafety, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of Religion: ſo we ſhall be blameleſſe before God, Angels and men, of all the evils, diſtractions and confuſions, which may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low upon or be occaſioned by the not ſatisfying of ſo juſt and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary deſires.</p>
            <p>And now for the reſult of the whole buſines: As we were before, and ſtill are ready to conſent and agree to the engaging &amp; acting in war, if we were ſatisfyed in our conſciences concerning the grounds of undertaking, and the means and ways of proſecuting the ſame, and concerning the other particulars contained in our Papers preſented to the Parliament: So not being ſatisfyed in thoſe, and looking upon the war as it is now ſtated, matters ſtanding as they do, and the whole complex buſineſſe taken together, We cannot but (with all dutifull reſpect &amp; honour both to his Majeſty and to the Eſtates of Parlia.) plainly diſſent and differ from the ſame, being ſo far from a cleer ſatisfaction in our conſciences concerning the lawfulneſſe and neceſſity of a War, upon the grounds and in the manner expreſſed in the Declaration of Parliament, that contrariwiſe we are cleerly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in our conſciences, it is an engagement of moſt dangerous conſequence to the true reformed Religion, both in Doctrine, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, Worſhip ond Government, prejudiciall to the due inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:124652:5"/>and liberty of the Kirk; favourable and advantagious to the Popiſh, Prelaticall, and Malignant party: inconſiſtent with the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Kingdom, and the ſatisfaction of the Presbyterian party in <hi>England;</hi> and therefore contrary to the Word of God, to the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Covenants, firſt Principles and publique Profeſſions of this Kirk and Kingdom, and a remedy worſe then the diſeaſe, and a courſe whereupon we cannot expect a bleſſing from God. For which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (expreſſed more fully and particularly in our Repreſentation upon the late Declaration of Parliament) we cannot in our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences allow either Miniſters in their places and callings, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers whatſoever, to concurre and cooperate in the Engagement: but truſt, that all that have in them true tenderneſſe of conſcience, and tremble at the Word of God, will by his grace and aſſiſtance keep themſelvs unſpotted and free in this buſines, and will chooſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction rather then iniquity, and take their hazard of ſuffering ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then of ſin, believing that the wrath of man ſhall turne to the praiſe of God, and <hi>the remainder of wrath He will reſtrain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We know there is much zeale pretended for the ends of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, uniformity of Religion, ſuppreſſion of Sectaries, and the like: But the more pretence be made of Religious ends, the Malignant deſignes varniſhed and painted therewith are unto God and good men ſo much the more hatefull. Doth the ſame fountain ſend forth both ſweet water and bitter? Or how can true zeale againſt Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, lodge in one breaſt with zeal for Malignants? Beſides, if Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and the Glory of God be now chiefly aimed at, what meaneth the refuſing of that ſatisfaction and ſecurity which hath been deſired for Religion? And if there be ſuch zeal againſt Sectaries in the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, what meant it, that not long ago, when the dangers of the true Reformed Religion in this Kirk, from the prevalent party of Sectaries in <hi>England</hi> were remonſtrat by us to the honourable Committee of Eſtates; it was pleaded by ſome, who now are moſt active and forward for an Engagement that this Kirk and Kingdom was in no ſuch danger from the Sectaries in <hi>England</hi> and the Army there, as might be any cauſe of not disbanding the Army in this Kingdom. And is this candid or faire dealing, to extenuat or ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat dangers from Sectaries, ſo as may beſt ſerve mens preſent buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes? Or if the deſign at that time was to disband that Army, as to make up another of their own modelling, why was this ſomuch diſclaimed when mentioned among our feares and apprehenſions in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:124652:5"/>our Romonſtrance, <hi>Octob.</hi> 13? However it ſeems the thing then ſuſpected is now begun to be acted, and it is too aparent that our former feares were not without ſome real ground.</p>
            <p>As to any calumnies or aſperſions caſt upon our proceedings by Malignant and diſaffected perſons: As our conſciences before God, ſo the very courſe of our proceedings before men doth cleerely wipe them off. And becauſe we have here onely ſummarily pointed at things, we ſhall for the cleerer underſtanding of all, refer to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Papers themſelves herewithall publiſhed and made known to all the people of God in this Land, that they may <hi>prove all things, and hold faſt that which is good.</hi> We do not doubt but upon a ſerious ſearch into the particulars, al that do ingeniouſly ſeek after ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall find it: And as it will appeare by the particular Papers, that we have not medled with Civil buſineſſes, but only with ſuch things as meerly concern the ſafety and ſecurity of Religion; So we leave it to the conſciences of all the wel-affected in the Land, whether they will give more credit and belief to the profeſſions and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of ſuch as were ſtrangers and enemies to the work and cauſe of God in the beginning, or of thoſe who have given conſtant and real proof of their integrity in this cauſe from the beginning? We truſt, God will diſcover more and more the myſtery of Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy now ſo ſtrongly working; manifeſt the innocency and ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his ſervants; deliver his people out of the preſent ſnares and guid them in a right and ſafe way: which afterwards ſhall be no griefe of heart, but matter of peace and comfort unto them.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. KER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="collection_of_parlimentary_documents">
            <div type="document">
               <head>The Parliaments Anſwer to the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Commiſſion of the General Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of the firſt of <hi>March.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>9. Martii. 1648.</hi> The Declaration of the Commiſſion of the Generall Aſſembly produced by Mr. <hi>Robert Dowglas</hi> accompanied with divers of the Miniſtry and Ruling Elders, read in audience of the Parliament.</head>
               <p>THE Eſtates of Parliament acknowledge, and takes well the continuance of their correſpondence in communicating this
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:124652:6"/>counſell or adviſe to the Parliament; and remits the ſame to be conſidered in their ſeverall bodies: but the Parliament deſires in the mean time, till the return of their anſwer (which they will do with all poſſible ſpeed) that the Commiſſioners of the Church would take no courſe for publiſhing or divulging the ſame. And de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares that as they conceive, this offer of Councell from the Church to the Parliament, doth not derogate from Parliamentary power and liberty: So by this delay or anſwer they do not mean any wayes to intrench upon the priviledge due to the Church or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion thereof: Their intention being meerly for preſervation of unity and good correſpondence betwixt them. <hi>Extractum.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Alex. Gibſon, <hi>Cler. Regiſt.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <head>Anſwer of the Commiſſion of the General Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to the Parliaments Paper of the 9. of <hi>March.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 
                     <date>10. <hi>Martii,</hi> 1648.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>THE Commiſſion of the Generall Aſſembly, having this day re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived under the hand of the Clerk Regiſter, the deſire of the Honourable Court of Parliament, concerning their Declaration pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to their Honours yeſterday.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Do humbly returne this Anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>AS we acknowledge it to be a great favour, that the Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Eſtates of Parliament do take well the continuance of our correſpondence, in communicating our counſell and advice to their Honours; and that they profeſſe their intention for preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Unity, and good correſpondence betwixt their Lordſhips and us, without intrenching any wayes upon he Priviledge and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Kirk. So we are neceſſitate humbly to repreſent to their Honours, that their deſire to us, (to take no courſe for publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing or divulging the ſaid Declaration till the return of their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer) is ſuch that this Kirk hath not been formerly acquainted with the like: Neither can we be anſwerable to the truſt put upon us by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:124652:6"/>God and the Generall Aſſembly, if we neglect or delay to emit and publiſh this Declaration, unleſſe we had aſſurance (which we have not) that there ſhould be no danger to the cauſe by the delay: Otherwiſe we come under great guiltineſſe, if we neglect to give timous and due warning not only to their Honours, but alſo to the whole Kingdome, as God requires of Watchmen in time of evident danger: Which made us, as before in like caſes we have done, to reſolve upon the Printing of the ſaid Declaration before we knew any thing of their Honours deſires for not publiſhing it.</p>
               <p>Thus having exonered our own conſciences, We humbly deſire their Honours to reſt confident, that as we are carefull to keep the liberty of the Kirk, ſo we ſhall be moſt unwilling to give to their Honours any cauſe of offence.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A. KER.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <head>The Diſſent and Proteſtation of ſome Members of Parliament, upon the Vote of Parliament of the <hi>16. March,</hi> concerning <hi>Berwick</hi> and <hi>Carlile.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHereas we have earneſtly deſired and preſſed that no power he granted to any Committee to do, act, or order any thing which may engage this Kingdome in a Warre, before the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament reſolve on a Warre, and ſtate the cauſe and the ends there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: It being in our judgment, neither agreeable to the Oath of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and tenour of Commiſſions from Shires and Burghs nor to the act of Parliament, 1640. againſt the Lords of the Articles, it being alſo of dangerous preparative, and much derogatory to the Liberties of the Kingdoms and Priviledges of Parliament: And most of all it being of exceeding dangerous conſequence to the cauſe of God, and the Ends of our Solemn League and Covenant; We do therefore diſſent from the granting of any ſuch power, and do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, that we may not be included in any ſuch Vote or Reſolution, but may be free before God and man of all the guiltineſſe, prejudices and evils that may follow thereupon to the Cauſe, Covenant and Religion, to the Kings perſon and Authority, to this Kirk and Kingdome, or to the Vnion betwext the Kingdoms.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:124652:7"/>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 
                     <date>22. <hi>Martii,</hi> 1648.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <head>To the Right Honorable the Eſtates of PARLIAMENT, The humble Deſires of the Commiſſioners of the General Aſſembly.</head>
               <p>WHereas we were deſired to appoint a conference with ſome of your Lordſhips which did go on towards an agreement, till it was obſtructed by a Vote of Parliament of the 16. of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant; And having already ſhown by our Papers of the 17. and 20. the reaſons of our not proceeding in that conference, and that the cauſe was not in us: We do now as the ſervants of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> for our own exoneration, for preventing of miſtakes, and for a cleare underſtanding between your Lordſhips and us, repreſent theſe our humble deſires which we recommend to your Lordſhips ſerious thoughts.</p>
               <p n="1">I. That the grounds and cauſes of undertaking a Warre may be cleared to be ſo juſt, as that all who are well affected may be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the lawfulneſſe and neceſſity of the engagement, and that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be acted in reference to a Warre, before the lawfulneſſe of the Warre and ſtate of the Queſtion be agreed upon.</p>
               <p n="2">II. That as the breaches of the Covenant by the prevalent party of Sectaries are evident, ſo we deſire and hope, that according to the Treaty it may be condiſcended upon and declared by the parliment, what are thoſe breaches of Peace which they take to be a ground of War, and that reparation thereof may be ſought.</p>
               <p n="3">III. That there may be no ſuch quarrel or ground of the War as may break the Union between the Kingdomes, or may diſcourage or diſoblige the Presbyterian party in <hi>England</hi> who continue firme in adhering to the League and Covenant.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:124652:7"/>
               <p n="4">IV. That if the Popiſh, Prelaticall, or Malignant party ſhall again riſe in Armes, this Nation and their Armies may be ſo farre from joyning or aſſociating with them, that one the contrary they may oppoſe them and endeavour to ſuppreſſe them, as enimies to this Cauſe and Covenant on the one hand, as well as Sectaries on the other.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Seeing your Lordſhips undertaking ſhould be in the firſt place for Religion; We deſire that his Majeſties late Conceſſions, and offers concerning Religion as they have been by the Church, ſo may be by the Parliament deelared unſatisfactory, whereby your Lordſhips may give further evidence of the reality of your intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the good and ſafty of Religion.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. That your Lordſhips may be pleaſed not to fix or ſettle upon any ſuch ſtate of a Queſtion, as doth not containe ſecurity to be had from his Majeſtie by his ſolemn Oath under his hand and ſeal, That he ſhall for Himſelfe and his Succeſſors, conſent and agree to Acts of Parliament enjoyning the League and Covenant, and fully eſtabliſhing Presbyterian Government, Directory of Worſhip and Confeſſion of Faith in all his Majeſties Dominions, and that his Majeſty ſhall never make oppoſition to any of theſe, or endeavour any change thereof: And that this ſecurity be had from his Majeſty before his Reſtitution to the exerciſe of his Royall power; Which deſire we propone for no other end but becauſe we cannot ſee how Religion, which hath been, and we truſt ſhall be, the principal end of all the undertakings of this Nation, can be otherwiſe ſecured, but that without this ſecurity, it ſhall be left in very great hazard.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. That for the ſame end of ſecuring Religion (which is profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be the principall cauſe of engagement) and for ſecuring all other ends of the Covenant, ſuch perſons only may be intruſted by your Lordſhips to be of your Committees and Armies, as have given conſtant proofe of their integrity and faithfulneſſe in this Cauſe, and againſt whom there is no juſt cauſe of exception or jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie; That ſo we may the more confidently encourage our Flocks, and Congregations to follow the Cauſe of God in their hands, and not to doubt of the fidelity of thoſe who ſhall be entruſted by your Lordſhips.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:124652:8"/>
               <p n="8">VIII. That there may be no engagement without a Solemn Oath, wherein the Church may have the ſame intereſt which they had in the Solemne League and Covenant, the Cauſe being the ſame.</p>
               <p>All which deſires being duely pondered by your Lordſhips in an equall balance, will we truſt be found juſt and neceſſary, and do not doubt but ſatisfaction from your Lordſhips therein may be a happy and effectuall meanes, for facilitating the ſtate of the Queſtion, and for uniting this Nation in an unanimous under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of ſuch duties, as are requiſite for the Reformation and defence of Religion, the Honour and Happineſſe of the King, the Peace and ſafty of the Kingdomes.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A. KER.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Edinb.</hi> 
                     <date>27. <hi>March,</hi> 1648.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <head>Anſwers of Parliament to the Deſires of the Commiſſioners of the General Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly repreſented by them to the Parliament.</head>
               <p>THe Eſtates of Parliament now conveened in this firſt Seſſion of the ſecond Trienniall Parliament, having conſidered the deſires of the Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſſembly, repreſented to them. They after full debate and conſideration concerning the ſame for anſwer to the firſt deſire.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Declares that the grounds and cauſes of undertaking of war, ſhall be cleared to be ſo juſt, as that all who are well affected may be ſatisfied in the lawfulneſſe and neceſſity of the engagement. And declares that they will be very carefull, that nothing be acted in reference to a warre during the conference, and untill the ſame be reported to the Parliament.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Item, For anſwer to the ſecond deſire. The Eſtates of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thinks fit, that the breaches of the Covenant and Treaties be repreſented. And the ſeeking of Reparation, and the beſt time and manner thereof conſidered, and appoints the Committee of twenty foure, or ſuch of their number as they ſhall appoint to do the ſame.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Item, For anſwer to the third deſire. The ſaid Eſtates of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:124652:8"/>declares, that this Kingdome will be ſo farre from making warre againſt the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> That any engagement they ſhall enter into, ſhall be for ſtrengthening the union betwixt the Kingdomes, And for encouraging the Presbyterians and well-affected in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Item,</hi> For anſwer to the fourth deſire, The Eſtates of Parliament agrees to the ſubſtance and matter of this fourth deſire. And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits to theſe who are to be upon the conference for ſtating the queſtion, to explaine the ſame.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Item,</hi> To the fiſt deſire. The Eſtates of Parliament for anſwer to this deſire, declares, That upon the agreement on the haill matter and ſtate of the queſtion, they will declare his Majeſties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions, concerning Religion not to be ſatisfactory.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Item,</hi> to the ſixt deſire. The Eſtates of Parliament for anſwer to this, declares. That ſince Religion hath been, and they truſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall be the principall end of all the undertakings of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. So they will be carefull that the preſent queſtion to be ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſhall containe ſecurity and aſſurance to be had from his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, be his ſolemne oath under his hand and ſeale. That he ſhall for himſelfe and his Succeſſors, give his Royall conſent to paſſe acts of Parliament, enjoyning the League and Covenant, eſtabliſhing Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Government, the Directory of worſhip, and Confeſſion of Faith in all his Majeſties Dominions, and that his Majeſtie ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver make any oppoſition to any of theſe, nor indeavour any change thereof. And as to that clauſe, <hi>viz.</hi> That this ſecurity be had from his Majeſtie before his reſtiution to the exerciſe of his Royall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. The Eſtates of Parliament remits this to theſe on the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, And who ſhall be appointed for drawing up the ſtate of the queſtion, To find out ſome more ſmooth expreſſion in place there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, with the like ſecurity to Religion.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Item,</hi> to the ſeventh deſire. The ſaid Eſtates of Parliament declares that they will be carefull that none ſhall be employed in the command of their Armies, nor in their Committees, But ſuch as are of known integrity and affection to the cauſe, and againſt whom there is no juſt caſe of exception.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> To the eighth Article or Deſire, The Eſtates of Parliament declares, That to the grounds of their engagement and undertak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Oath ſhall be ſubjoyned wherein both in the framing of it and otherwayes the Church ſhall have their due intereſt, And the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:124652:9"/>Eſtates of Parliament deſires the Commiſſion of the Church, To appoint ſome of their number to meet with ſuch of that Committee of Parliament of 24. As ſhall be appointed by the ſame Committee for the conference and ſtating of the queſtion, for agreeing upon the grounds of an engagement, and drawing up ſuch a ſtate of a queſtion as may unite this Nation in an unanimous undertaking of ſuch duties as are requiſite for the Reformation and defence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the ſafety, honour and happineſſe of the King and his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and the good of this Kingdome. <hi>Extract forth out of the Books of Parliament, By me Sir Alexander Gibſon of Durie Knight, Clerk of his Majeſties Regiſters Councel and Rolls under my ſigne and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription Manuel.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Alex. Gibſon, Cler, Regiſt.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Edinburgh.</hi> 
                     <date>29. <hi>Martii.</hi> 1648.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <head>A humble Repreſentation of the ſenſe of the Commiſſioners of the General Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, To the Honourable Eſtates of Parli. upon their L. Anſwer to the eight Deſires lately preſented to their Lordſhips.</head>
               <p>HAving received yeſterday the Anſwer of the Honourable E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of Parliament to our late Deſires preſented to their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips upon the 22. of this inſtant; We did immediately take to our conſideration the particular anſwers given thereunto; And now without any longer delay do humbly repreſent to their Honours our ſenſe of the Particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As to the Anſwer of the firſt Deſire, we conceive that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any thing expreſſed in your Lordſhips Anſwer there may be an acting in reference to a warre before the lawfulneſſe of the Warre and the ſtate of the queſtion be agreed upon, which is the very thing we did deſire to be avoided.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the Anſwer to our ſecond Deſire, we neither finde any brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of peace between the Kingdomes which may be a ground of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:124652:9"/>war, condeſcended upon, nor any poſitive reſolution of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſeek reparation thereof according to the Treaties, yet both theſe were deſired by us.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In the anſwer to the third deſire, inſtead of that clauſe of the deſire, <hi>The Presbyterian party in England, who continue firme in adhering to the League and Covenant,</hi> we finde this change of expreſſion in the Anſwers, <hi>The Presbyterians and well-affected in England;</hi> which as the words ſtand may intimate and ſuppoſe, that there are ſome well-affected in <hi>England,</hi> which are not of the Presbyterian party, nor do adhere to the League and Covenant.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Our fourth deſire for not joyning or aſſociating what the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh, Prelaticall or malignant party, if they ſhall againe riſe in Armes, and that it may be endeavoured to ſuppreſſe them as ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the cauſe and Covenant on the one hand, as well as Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries upon the other; being ſo juſt in it ſelfe, ſo conſonant to the former principles and profeſſions of this Kirke and Kingdome, ſince their firſt engagement in this cauſe; and being alſo as cleare both in the matter and expreſſion, as the Covenant, Treaties, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations of both Kingdomes, we cannot conceive wherein it needs explanation, or what doubt or ſcruple can be made concerning it as it ſtands, unleſſe there be now ſome more favourable and friendly intentions towards the malignant party then formerly, which wee pray the Lord to avert: And although it is too manifeſt that ſome plead for Malignants, as if they were to be joyned with as friends, rather then avoided as enemies to the cauſe (whereof we have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken more fully in our late Declaration) yet we truſt that any ſuch deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gne is and ſhall be far from the thoughts and intentions of the Honourable Court of Parliament.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Touching the 5 Deſire, as your Lordſhips answers ems to ſupp ſe his Maje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>late conceſſions concerning Religion, not to be ſatisfactory, ſo theſe conceſſions being ſo prejudicial to the cauſe &amp; Covenant; We wiſh your Lordſhips had been pleaſed to declare againſt them both poſitively without any condition, and preſently without any delay.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In the anſwer to the ſixt deſire, as thereis much ſaid in the firſt part for ſecurity of Religion to be had from his Majeſty, ſo that clauſe, viz. <hi>That this ſecurity be had from his Majeſty before his reſtitution to the exerciſe of his royall tower</hi> not being agreed to by your Lordſhips, but rather laid aſide untill ſome ſmoother expreſſions be found out; We are left unſatisfied in that which is the maine of that deſire, and cannot be aſſured of any ſecurity expreſſed in the firſt part of your
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:124652:10"/>Lordſhips anſwer If your Lordſhips had been pleaſed to condeſcend upon another expreſſion containing as good and as reall ſecurity for Religion, wee ſhould have acquieſſed therein without ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon words, but there being no other expreſſion yet condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon, and that clauſe of ours (without which the whole deſire is leſt uncertain) laid aſide for the preſent; We cannot finde our ſelves therein ſatisfied as yet.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The anſwer to the ſeventh Deſire, concerning ſuch as are to be truſted in Armies, and Committees, doth omit ſome of the qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations expreſſed in our Deſire, viz. <hi>Such as have given conſtant proofe of their integrity and faithfulneſſe in this cauſe, and againſt whom there is no juſt cauſe of jealouſie, that ſo we may the more confidently encourage our flockes to follow the cauſe of God in their hands, and not to doubt of their fidelity;</hi> Which qualifications being contained in our Deſire, and omitted in your Lordſhips Anſwers; We are not without feares that this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion may be made uſe of by ſome, as if your Lordſhips had not meant to agree fully to that deſire, and ſo take occaſion to deale for employing and entruſting ſuch in the Committees and Armies, as may be juſtly excluded by the qualifications contained in our ſaid Deſire.</p>
               <p>In the anſwer to the laſt Deſire, in ſtead of that cleare expreſſion uſed by us, namely, <hi>That the Kirke may have the ſame intereſt in any oath for a new engagement which they had in the ſolemne League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant;</hi> We finde this doubtfull and uncertaine expreſſion, <hi>The Kirke ſhall have their due intereſts.</hi> Which difference of your Lordſhips expreſſion from ours, may alſo be interpreted by ſome, as if the Kirk had aſſumed more intereſt in the League and Covenant, than was due unto them.</p>
               <p>Unto theſe, and the like conſiderations, Wee humbly conceive that our Deſires, unto which we ſtill adhere as juſt and neceſſary, are not ſatisfied by your Lordſhips Anſwer: And without cleare ſatisfaction in theſe deſires, We finde it not ſafe to appoint a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference for agreeing upon the ſtate of a queſtion for War: yet if your Lordſhips had deſired, or doe deſire further conference with ſome of our number for ſatisfaction of our above mentioned Deſires, Wee ſhould have yeelded, and yet ſhall willingly yeeld thereunto. And as the preſent want of ſatisfaction in theſe Deſires doth retard and hinder our proceedings towards an agreement upon the ſtate of a queſtion; ſo we are ſtill confident that a reall and cleare ſatisfaction to the ſaid deſires, may be a happy and effectuall meanes for facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:124652:10"/>the ſtate of the queſtion, and for uniting this Nation in an unanimous undertaking of ſuch duties, as are requiſite for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and defence of Religion, the ſafety, honour, and happineſſe of the King and his poſterity, and the good, peace, and ſafety of the Kingdomes.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A. KER.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <head>A Paper from the Parliament of the <hi>29 March, 1648.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>At <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 
                     <date>the 29 day of <hi>March,</hi> the yeare of God 1648 yeares;</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>WHereas the Commiſſioners of the Church have this day exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited to the Parliament one paper intituled an humble repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of the ſenſe of the Commiſſioners of the General Aſſembly; To the honourable Eſtates of Parliament upon their Lordſhips an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the eight Deſires lately preſented to their Lordſhips: And the ſame being read in audience of the Eſtates of Parliament, They or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain the former Committee of 24 to confer with the Commiſſioners of the Church, or any whom they ſhall appoint upon the papers exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited by the Church, and anſwers given thereto by the Parliament, and appointed them to debate thereupon, and for removing all diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and alſo upon the ſtate of the queſtion and whole matter: And ordaines this to be communicated to the Commiſſioners of the Church in anſwer to the paper exhibited by them to the Parliament this day. And deſires that the Commiſſioners of the Kirke, or thoſe whom they ſhall appoint may come authorized with the like power to confer. <hi>Extract.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>ALEX. GIBSON, Cler. Regiſtri.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <head>The Anſwer of the Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſſembly, <hi>Edin. penult. Mar.</hi> 1648.</head>
               <p>THE Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſſembly, having this day received a power from the Honourable Eſtates of Parliament, deſiring a conference upon our late Deſires, and the Parliaments anſwer given thereunto, and alſo upon the ſtate of the queſtion, and whole matter, doe humbly returne this Anſwer:</p>
               <p>That as we have been, ſo we are ſtill willing to appoint a confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:124652:11"/>upon the eight Deſires lately preſented to your Lordſhips, and upon the unſatisfactorineſſe of your Lordſhips anſwer thereunto: And if your Lordſhips ſhall yet be pleaſed to give reall and cleare ſatisfaction to our ſaid deſires, We ſhall immediately thereupon appoint ſome of our number to confer with a Committee of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament upon the ſtate of the queſtion. This inſiſting upon ſatisfaction to our deſires, before we appoint a conference upon the ſtate of the queſtion, doth not proceed from any peremptorineſſe about words, or things of ſmall moment, nor from any partiality, or ſelf inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, nor from any inclination to ſtretch our ſelves beyond our line, nor from intention to obſtruct any lawfull endeavours, either for Monarchicall government in the Kings Majeſty and his poſterity, or for preferring oppoſing and ſuppreſſing of Sectaries: Our record is in heaven, we abhor and deteſt all ſuch wayes: But our reall purpoſe is to keep our ſelves ſo free, that in an implicit way we conſent not to, nor concur in ſtating of a queſtion of War, before we ſee the ſafety and ſecurity of Religion ſufficiently provided for, being tender of the great truſt committed to us, as the ſervants of <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> and officers of his Kingdome, for preſerving the precious Jewell of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which ought to be as well to your Lordſhips as to us, above all worldly intereſts.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A. KER.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <head>The Article of the Demands which is to be communicated to the Commiſsioners of the Church, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THAT an effectuall courſe be taken by the Houſes for enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Covenant to be taken by all the Subjects of the Crowne of <hi>England</hi> conforme to the firſt Article-of the Treaty, and conform to the Declaration of both Kingdomes in <hi>anno</hi> 1643. By which all who would not take the Covenant, were declared to be publicke enemies to Religion and the Countrey: And that they are to bee cenſured and puniſhed as profeſſed Adverſaries and Malignants: And that reformation of, and uniformity in Religion, be ſettled according to the Covenant; That as the Houſes of Parliament have agreed to the Directory of worſhip, ſo they would take a reall courſe for the practiſing thereof by all the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> That the Confeſſion of Faith tranſmitted from the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> to the Houſes be approved: And that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:124652:11"/>Presbyteriall government with a ſubordination of the lower Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies to the higher, be ſetled, and fully eſtabliſhed in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> And that effectuall courſe be taken for ſuppreſſing and extirpating all Hereſies and Schiſmes, particularly Socinianiſme, Arminianiſme, Arrianiſme, Anabaptiſme, Antinomianiſme, Erra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſme, Familiſme, Browniſme, and Independency; and for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting what is yet further to be done, for extirpating Popery and Prelacy, and ſuppreſſing the practice of the Service-book, common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called the Book of Engliſh Common-prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>2 <hi>Aprilis</hi> 1648.</label>
               </p>
               <p>This Article read and agreed to, by the Eſtates of Parliament, is thought fitting to bee demanded of the Parliament of <hi>England:</hi> And the Eſtates appoints the ſeventh Article to be communicate to the Commiſſioners of the Kirk, that they may return their thoughts thereupon, either for addition or alteration, which the Parliament will take to their conſideration. And the Eſtates appoints the Lord <hi>Balmerinoth,</hi> Lord <hi>Huniby,</hi> and <hi>Archbald Sydſerſe,</hi> to acquaint the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of the Church therewith. <hi>Extracted forth of the Records of Parliament, and Articles of breaches of the Covenant and Treaties, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands for reparation thereof, reſpective by me, Sir</hi> Alex. Gibſon <hi>of</hi> Dure, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Alex. Gibſon <hi>Cler. Regiſt.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Edinb. <date>13 Aprilis, 1648.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <head>The humble returne of the Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſſembly unto that Article of the Demands concerning Religion, and the Covenant, &amp;c. communicated unto them by the Honourable Eſtates of Parliament.</head>
               <p>AS there is nothing which the Kirke of <hi>Scotland</hi> now for a long time hath more earneſtly wiſhed, and ſeriouſly ſtudyed, then the ſettling of Religion, and carrying on of the worke of unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in all the three Kingdomes; ſo it is ſtill our deſire that your Lordſhips ſhould ſincerely and really endeavour the ſame in all fair and lawfull wayes both with the King and Parliament of <hi>England</hi> according to the League and Covenant. As to the Article commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated unto us, we ſhall not ſearch after the cauſe why your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips have changed the way formerly uſed of ſending Propoſitions to his Majeſtie, without whoſe confidence your Lordſhips will eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge, that the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> cannot render the particulars contained in the demand effectuall for ſecuring of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Neither ſhall we inſiſt upon the prejudice, that preparative
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:124652:12"/>of the taking of reſolutions in that which concernes Religion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the advice and conſent of the Kirke, may bring to the intereſt and liberty thereof. But conceiving that wee have juſt reaſon to looke upon the demand as intended to be a ground of warre, in caſe the Sea-men ſhall be refuſed by the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not returne our thoughts thereupon, untill your Lordſhips ſhall be pleaſed to give us a ſatisfactory anſwer to our eight deſires, formerly propounded to your Lordſhips, and untill you ſhall be pleaſed alſo to acquaint us with the Articles of the breaches of the Covenant and Treaties, and other demands, for reparation thereof, mentioned in the paper ſent to us: that ſo we may not only know that no other of the demands doe croſſe this, or tend to the hinderance of the work of Reformation, but alſo that we may be ſatisfied in our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces upon the whole matter, and be aſſured that all things are ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and reſolved, as may indeed contribute for eſtabliſhing the Covenant, and ſettling of Reformation of, and Uniformitie in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and attaining all things expreſſed in your Lordſhips demands communicated to us. In the meane while ſeeing your Lordſhips do profeſſe that the Cauſe is the ſame, and the cheif ground of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking is for Religion; Wee deſire your Lordſhips ſeriouſly in your conſciences to ponder, how yee can make the refuſall of this demand a cauſe of warre againſt the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> with whom this nation was lately ingaged in a warre in defence of the League and Covenant, and ends thereof, when the King was in armes againſt both, and yet ingage in a warre for the King, while he ſtill refuſes to ſettle Religion and injoyn the Covenant, and will come no further at the uttermoſt, then to leave the Sea-men Arbitrary, as is evident from his late conceſſions; Or how your Lordſhips can propound any ſuch demand unto others whilſt your ſelves have not declared the Kings conceſſions ſo much as unſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, ſeeing theſe conceſſions are diſtructive to moſt of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars contained in your Lordſhips demands.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Edinb. <date>
                        <hi>18</hi> Aprill, <hi>1648.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <head>To the Right honourable, and High Court of Parliament, The humble Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of the Commiſſioner of the Generall Aſſembly.</head>
               <p>REligion being of all things the moſt excellent, as it hath been the principall end of all the in deavours and undertakings of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:124652:12"/>this Nation, ſo it is the main ſubject of our thoughts and cares, and we truſt is moſt in the hearts of all the faithfull Miniſters and godly people throughout the Land, as ſeverall of their ſupplications un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Lordſhips do make evident. It was from the tender regard we had of this ſo precious a jewell, that we did emit a Declaration con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning preſent dangers, and duties; And it was alſo from our reſpect thereunto, perceiving your Lordſh. inclined to an ingagement, from which wee neither were then, nor now are averſe (being firſt ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the grounds of the undertaking, and in the way of the manag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame) that we did afterwards propound ſome humble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires unto your Lordſhips, containing things neceſſary for a right undertaking for, and ſecuring of Religion, and preſerving the Vnion between the Kingdomes: But after long attendance, and moſt earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt expectation, having received no ſatisfaction from your Lordſhips in theſe our deſires; and conceiving that your Lordſhips reſolutions are towards an ingagement in a warre, We doe from no other prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and intention, then the love of the truth, and the diſcharge of the truſt committed unto us, as the ſervants of the living God, and his ſon Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall judge the quicke and the dead; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate and obteſt your Lordſhips, that as you doe profeſſe that any undertakings which yee now are, or ſhall bee neceſſitated unto, ſhall onely be for ſettling Religion, Truth and peace under His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Government, So for convinceing our conſciences and all the faithfull Miniſters and people of God in both Kingdomes, of the integrity of your intentions, that your Lordſhips will be pleaſed to give us ſatisfaction, in all theſe our former juſt and neceſſary deſires, and that for the ſaid end, your Lordſhips wil make it appear that you meane to be far from intereſſing your ſelves in any thing, that may put in His Majeſties hands ſuch power as may not onely bring the by-gon proceedings of both Kingdomes in the League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in queſtion, but alſo for the time to come make void all the authority of Parliaments, though proceeding never ſo rightly in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to Religion, and Liberties of the Kingdoms; And that your Lordſhips will be pleaſed to make it manifeſt, that you will be ſo farre from aſſociating with, or giving truſt and countenance to any within the three Kingdoms, who do not ſwear and ſubſcribe the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne League and Covenant, That on the contrary your Lordſhips will hold them all for profeſſed Adverſaries, and Malignants, and indeavour to ſuppreſſe them if they riſe in Armes; Which we think
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:124652:13"/>we may with the greater reaſon and confidence expect from your Lordſhips, becauſe yee have reſolved to demand of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> that an effectuall courſe be taken by the Houſes for injoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Covenant to be taken by all the Subjects of the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> Conforme to the firſt Article of the Treaty, &amp; the Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of both Kingdomes in <hi>anno</hi> 1643, By which all who would not take the Covenant, were Declared to be publique enemies to Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the Countrie, and that they are to be cenſured and puniſhed as profeſſed Adverſaries and Malignants; And we truſt, that whilſt your Lordſhips require of them the performance of duties contained in the Treaties and Declaration, you will make it appeare that you intend to do nothing your ſelves contrary thereunto, The obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therein being equall in regard of both, and the performance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like conducing for Religion and the Covenant. And we doe humbly intreate that your honours will be pleaſed to make known unto us your reſolutionsupon the whole matter, that we may ſee there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing therein that may croſſe your Lordſhips demands concerning Religion, and be inconſiſtent with the ſecurity thereof and our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire for the ſame: And that what ſhall be thought fitting to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> concerning Religion, for rendering the ſame the more effectuall, your Lordſhips will at the ſame time ſolicite His Majeſty for His Royall aſſent thereunto, that His Majeſty and all others may know, that what you intend on His behalfe, is with a ſubordination to thoſe ends, And ſo his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty may be induced to remove al obſtructions on his part, that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſettling of Religion, and his Majeſties Government. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſirous that all meanes bee firſt aſſaid which may prevent the effuſion of more Chriſtian blood, ſo farre as is poſſible, Therefore as the meſſengers of peace, we doe ſupplicate that your Lordſhips will take ſuch courſe for ſeeking reparation from the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> as may bee moſt probable in reaſon to obtaine the ſame in a peaceable way. And finally wee expect that your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips will do nothing that may ſtrengthen the Popiſh, Prelaticall, or Malignant party, who are waiting for their day, or that may diſcourage or weaken the Presbyterian party in <hi>England,</hi> or render your wayes ſuſpitions unto them: but that your Lordſhips will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy all the power which God hath put in your hand for advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his honour, and the Kingdome of his Sonne. Many of your Lordſhips have been inſtrumentall in as glorious a worke of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:124652:13"/>as any age hath ſeen, and all of your have been witneſſes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and if any thing ſhall proceed from you for weakening or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feating thereof, as it will bee matter of high provocation againſt the Lord, ſo doubtleſſe it wil be trouble to your ſoules in your lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end, and meet you in the day of your accounts. And if your Lordſhips ſhall refuſe to hearken to this our humble ſupplication; we take God to record that we have exonoured our ſelves as in his ſight, and that we, and the Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi> whoſe truſt we diſcharge in the publique affaires thereof, are free of all that guilt that ſhall follow upon any undertakings or reſolutions, tending to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of Religion, the honour and happines of the King, and the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and peace of the Kingdoms. But we deſire to perſwade our ſelves better things of your Lorſhips, and that you will give us ſuch ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction as may incourage us to bear reall teſtimony of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, that ye intend the ſettling of Religion, and the carrying on of all things in ſuch a way, as may contribute for the ſecuring of the ſame,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <head>The diſſent and proteſtation of ſome Members of Parliament againſt their Lordſhips proceeding to a determination in the Declaration concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the breaches, and demands, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>WHereas the draught of a Declaratian hath now beene read concerning the breaches of the Covenant, in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and the demands to bee made for remedy and reparation thereof, the dangers to Religion, and the duties whereunto we are oblieged by Covenant for Reformation and Uniformity in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the ſecurity to be had for eſtabliſhing the ſame, upon which grounds a warre is principally founded: And whereas we have ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſired and inſiſted. That there may bee no proceeding to any determination concerning the ſaid Declaration before the Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſſembly be firſt conſulted therein, We do hereby enter our diſſent, from proceeding to the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of matters ſo highly concerning Religion, without the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and concurrence of the Kirke, as a preparative of moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conſequence to Religion, and deſtructive to the liberties of the Church, as contrary to the National &amp; Solemn League &amp; Covenant, and to the known lawes and conſtant practices of this Kingdome; And we do proteſt that we may not be included in any ſuch vote or reſolution, but may be free of al the guiltines, confuſions diſtractions and evill whatſoever that may follow thereupon to Religion, the King, this Kirk and Kingdom, And the union betwixt the Kingdoms.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:124652:14"/>
               <head>The Reaſons of the aforeſaid Proteſtation.</head>
               <p>THat the Parliament ought to take into conſideration the papers already preſented by the Kirke, and adviſe with them concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the draught of the Declaration, before they approve the ſame, for the Reaſons following:
<list>
                     <item>1. The chiefe ſubject of the Declaration, is concerning the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Covenant in matters of Religion, and the demands to be made for remedy and reparation thereof, the dangers of Religion, with the duties whereunto we are oblieged by Covenant, for Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and uniformity in Religion, and the ſecurity to be had for the eſtabliſhment of the ſame: And ſo much the more the Kirke is to be conſulted therein, that upon theſe grounds chiefly, a warre is founded, concerning the lawfulneſſe whereof, the advice of the Kirke ought to bee taken, the grounds being taken principally from the intereſt of Covenant and Religion.</item>
                     <item>2. It is acknowledged and declared, by the Laws of the Kingdome in ſeverall Acts of Parliament, that the Aſſemblies of this Kirke, are the competent and proper Judges, againſt all matters Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall: And when there were greateſt controverſies in matters of Religion betwixt his Majeſty and this Kingdome; that which was earneſtly ſought for, as the proper and only mean to put an end to all differences touching matters of Religion, and aſſented to by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty in a ſolemne agreement, was, that all queſtions about Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and matters Eccleſiaſticall, be determined by the Aſſemblies of the Kirke, as matters Civill by the Parliament: which expreſſe words are ſet down in the 4 and 38 Acts of Parliament, 1640 and by many Acts of Parliament, it is particularly acknowledged, that in matters of Religion, the antecedent judgement is the Kirke, and the conſequent judgement or Civil ſanction, is the States, as in the Kings oath of Coronation, and the firſt act 1592. anent the liberties of the Kirke, inſerted in our Nationall Covenant, and repeated in the act reſciſſory 1640. which evinceth that the Parliament ſhould communicate the Declaration to the Kirke, before they reſolve up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it among themſelves.</item>
                     <item>3. All our Supplications, Remonſtrances, Declarations Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Acts of Aſſembly and Parliament, and our defenſive Armes, in <hi>anno</hi> 1639, and 1640, were not onely againſt the Innovations then urged, in the book of Canons, Service book &amp;c. for the evill matter therein contained; but alſo againſt the dangerous manner of introducing the ſame, without the advice and conſent of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:124652:14"/>Aſſemblies of the Kirke, and Lawes of the Kingdome.</item>
                     <item>4. Our Nationall Covenant, and our Solemne League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant were firſt drawne by the Kirke: And their intereſt interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation thereof, eſpecially ſo far as concernes Religion, was never hitherto denyed: but by the conſtant practice of this Kingdome, the Aſſemblies of the Kirke were alwayes conſulted, anent the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers thereunto, and the duties grounded thereupon, and touching the demands and ſecurity for Religion, before any expedition or Declaration for War, offenſive or defenſive.</item>
                     <item>5. The Parliaments aſſuming to themſelves the ſole judging of the breaches of Covenants, demands for reparation, the dangers to, duties for, and ſecurity of Religion, is a moſt dangerous prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and deſtructive to the liberties of the Kirk; for ſubſequent Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments may according to this preſident, without the advice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Aſſemblies of the Kirke, impoſe upon them new Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Faith, formes of worſhip and Church government, and ſo change the very ſubſtance and fundamentals of our Religion; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe this preparative in a Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> will confirme ſuch in their opinions and practices, in the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> who maintaine the Erraſtian tenets: wherefore if extirpation of Erraſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſme be intended in <hi>England,</hi> as is profeſſed, it ſhould not be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at home.</item>
                     <item>6. Even the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> would not ingage in the League and Covenant, untill they had firſt adviſed it with the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of Divines in point of conſcience, albeit that Aſſembly hath no juriſdiction; how much more ſhould we be cautions of ingaging in ſuch a buſineſſe, where there is a conſtituted ſettled Church, without their advice.</item>
                     <item>7. It were a manifeſt breach both of our Nationall Covenant, and of the Solemne League and Covenant to determine or approve of a buſineſſe ſo highly concerning Religion, without the advice and concurrence of the Generall Aſſembly, or their Commiſſioners, ſeeing by both Covenants we are plainly oblieged, to preſerve and maintaine the doctrine, diſcipline, and government of the Kirke, which yet cannot be preſerved, but overthrowne by ſuch a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary determination and Declaration, concerning the Covenant and Religion, without the advice and conſent of the Kirke. Neither can we expect the bleſſing of God upon our undertakings, if in this cauſe, wherein the honour and glory of God, and the good of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is ſo highly concerned, we ſhould engage without the advice
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:124652:15"/>and concurrence of the faithfull Miniſters of this Kirke, whom God hath uſed as maine inſtruments in the beginning and progreſſe of the worke of Reformation.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Edinb. <date>20. April 1648.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <head>Anſwers of the Parliament to the deſires given in to them by the Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſſembly, and to the papers given in by them upon the <hi>13</hi> and <hi>18</hi> dayes of this month.</head>
               <p>THe Eſtates of Parliament having againe taken to their conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration the deſires given in to them by the Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſſembly: And having alſo conſidered the papers given in by the ſaid Commiſſioners upon the 13 and 18 dayes of this month, doe conceive that the Declaration of Parliament is a full and ſatisfactory anſwer to the firſt eight Deſires. As alſo to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two papers in ſo far as the ſame are concident with theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires: And as to the other particulars of their two laſt papers, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the way and time of ſending Propoſitions to the King.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is anſwered, That the Parliament conceives the ſame way is now taken that hath been formerly: And in regard the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> have laid aſide theſe Propoſitions concerning Religion, and the joynt intereſt of the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> We are neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to make our firſt applications to them who muſt firſt agree and condeſcend thereunto before his Majeſties aſſent can be demanded: And that it evidently appeares by the Declaration, that we really in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to inſiſt for ſatisfaction from his Majeſty in that that concernes Religion before all worldly things: And that ſo ſoon as his Majeſty ſhall be in ſuch a condition of freedome, honour, and ſafety, as his conceſſions may be effectuall. And as to that prejudice alleadged in the preparative of taking reſolutions in that which concernes Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, without advice and conſent of the Kirke.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is anſwered, That as we have never hitherto taken any reſolutions in that which concerns Religion without advice of the Kirke: And ſince, what is now declared by the Parliament in order to Religion, is not upon any new grounds, but in purſuance of the ſame grounds contained in the Covenant, in the Acts of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Aſſembly and Acts of Parliament: And that in our demands concerning Religion, as the advice of the Commiſſioners of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly hath been deſired; ſo we ſhall never doe any thing that may prejudice the juſt intereſt and liberty of the Kirke of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:124652:15"/>
               <p>And for their deſire to be ſatisfied in the whole matter, It is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, That it is cleare by the Declaration which containes the grounds and reſolutions of the Parliament on the whole matter, That there is nothing therein which doth croſſe the demands con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Religion, or is inconſiſtent with the ſecurity thereof.</p>
               <p>And farther, It is ordained that the Parliament having agreed unto the Declaration, it be communicated to the Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſſembly before it be publiſhed; and in matters that concernes Religion, that the Parliament will be ready to heare and conſider the advice of the Commiſſioners of the Kirke. <hi>Extract. out of the bookes of Parliament, by Sir</hi> Alex Gibſon <hi>of</hi> Dury <hi>Knight, Clerk of his Majeſties Regiſters, Councell and Rolls, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Alex. Gibſon, <hi>Cler. Regiſt.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Edinb. <date>25. April 1648.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <head>The humble returne of the Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſſembly to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of the Honourable and high Court of Parliament to our <hi>8</hi> Deſires, and to our papers of the <hi>13</hi> and <hi>18</hi> of this Month.</head>
               <p>WHereas your Lordſhips did communicate unto us your large Declaration, containing principally your Lordſhips reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions concerning dangers and duties relating to Religion, we wiſh your Lordſhips had been ſo tender of the liberty and due intereſt of the Gen. Aſſembly &amp; their Commiſſioners, as to have communicated to us a buſines ſo highly concerning Religion before, not after your Lordſhips reſolutions taken therein; And that your Lordſhips had not given juſt cauſe to ſo many &amp; ſo conſiderable Members of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, who have given moſt reall and conſtant teſtimony of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity in this cauſe, to diſſent from, and proteſt againſt your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips proceeding to determine a buſineſſe of this nature, without conſultation with us, and our conſent had therein. For our part, the truſt committed to us is ſo precious, that we may not hold our peace in ſuch a caſe, but muſt freely profeſſe and declare to your Lordſhips, That this Act being really a taking from us to your ſelves, the antecedent judgement and determination of danger, sand duties, ſo highly concerning Religion in this preſent juncture of affaires; the liberties of the Kirke are ſo far prejudiced as could not have entered into our hearts to expect, after ſo ſolemne obligations to preſerve and maintaine the Doctrine, Diſcipline, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kirke of <hi>Scotland;</hi> We therefore proteſt for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:124652:16"/>of the Liberties of this Kirk according to the word of God, Solemn Covenants, former lawes and laudable cuſtomes of this Kirk and Kingdome, and that this act of your Lordſhips be no prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive for the future Finally that it ſhall be yet free unto us, according to the duties of our place, and as there ſhall bee cauſe, to give our judgements in an Eccleſiaſticall way, of the materialls of the ſaid Declaration, ſo far as Religion is therein concerned, as freely as if your Lordſhips had taken no reſolution thereupon.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being premiſed, And deſiring your Lordſhips to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what we did formerly profeſſe in our late petition, that we never were, nor now are averſe from any Ingagement, being firſt ſatisfied in the grounds of undertaking, and in the way of manag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame, Wee proceed to make our humble returne to your Lordſhips anſwer of the 20th of this month to our eight deſires, and our papers of the 13th and 18th of the ſame month.</p>
               <p>Whereas your Lordſhips conceive that your Declaration commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated unto us, is a full and ſatisfactory anſwer to our eight deſires, we muſt clearly profeſſe to your Lordſhips, that we can find no ſuch thing in that Declaration as a ſatisfaction to our eight deſires, But that we find diverſe things in it, which we humbly conceive to be very prejudiciall to theſe our deſires, and of very dangerous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to the Cauſe of God and the Solemne League and Covenant. And for the particulars wee ſhall expreſſe our ſenſe thereof in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct paper as ſoon as we can put our thoughts in order, which we hope ſhall be very ſhortly.</p>
               <p>As to our other two papers, give us leave to put your Lordſhips in mind of ſome particulars contained therein, which we obſerve not to be touched, much leſſe ſatisfied by your Lordſhips, either in your anſwer of the 20th. Or in the Declaration, as namely.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In our paper of the 13th we deſired your Lordſhips ſeriouſly to ponder how you can make the refuſall of that demand concerning Religion, a cauſe of warre againſt the Parliament of <hi>England?</hi> with whom this Nation was lately ingaged in a warre for defence of the League and Covenant, and the end thereof, when the King was in Armes againſt both: And yet ingage in a warre for the King whilſt he refuſeth to give ſatisfaction in that which concerns Religion and the Covenant, and will come no further at the utmoſt, then to leave the ſame arbitrary: Shall the refuſall of one and the ſame deſire, in the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> be a cauſe of warre, and yet in the King not ſo much as an impediment, to aſſiſtance, even whilſt wee
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:124652:16"/>have juſt cauſe to feare that he will imploy his power againſt the Cauſe and Covenant?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Neither do we find any anſwer to that part of our petition of the 18th which concerneth his Majeſties negative voyce, there ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed under the name of ſuch power as may not only bring the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon proceedings of both Kingdomes in the League and Covenant in queſtion, but alſo for the time to come, make void all the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parliaments though proceeding never ſo rightly in refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Religion, &amp; liberties of the Kingdoms which made us deſire your Lord hips might be far from intere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing your ſelves in any thing that may put ſuch a power in his Majeſties hands.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We have received no anſwer to that part of the ſame petition, wherein it was deſired that if any within the three Kingdomes who doe not ſweare and ſubſcribe the Solemn League and Covenant, riſe in Armes, your Lordſhips will hold them all for profeſſed Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Malignants, and indeavour to ſuppreſſe them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Nor find we nay thing in your Lordſhips anſwer or Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in reference to that clauſe of our petition that your Lordſhips may let His majeſty and al others know that what you intend on his behalfe, is with a ſubordmation to Religion, and the ſecurity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p>Some particulars in theſe two papers your Lordſhips are pleaſed to make anſwer unto. And firſt to that which we deſired concerning applications to be made to the Kings Majeſty, as well as to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>England,</hi> for ſatisfaction in point of Religion, your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips anſwer, That the Parliament conceives the ſame way is now taken that hath been formerly, which we doe not underſtand to be ſo, not having knowne heretofore ſuch a way of ſending demands of this nature to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> but that the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> were always deſired to concur with this Kingdom, in the ſending of Propoſitions to his Majeſty, And whatſoever the Houſes of Parliament have done in laying aſide diverſe of the Propoſitions concerning Religion, formerly agreed upon by both Kingdomes, yet we conceive it is ſtill the duty of this Kingdome, to inſiſt with His Majeſty upon their juſt and laudable deſires, for ſettling the Reformation and uniformity of Religion according to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, for the reaſons and ends expreſſed in our petition And ſo much the rather becauſe after ſo many unſatisfactory anſwers and meſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges from his Majeſty, we doe not expect a right underſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween His Majeſty and his people, till ſomewhat proceeds from him
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:124652:17"/>towards a cleare ſatisfaction of the juſt deſires of his people, and eſpecially in point of Religion. And although his Majeſty bee not preſently in that condition, as that hee may make a perfect ſettlement of Religion, yet wee know not why even in the condition he now is in, there may not be applications made to him, for obtaining from him ſecurity, and aſſurance for the ſettling of Religion according to the Covenant. And whereas your Lordſhips by that which followeth in your anſwer, let us know that you ſuſpend your inſiſting for ſatisfaction from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty in Religion, till hee ſhall bee in ſuch a condition of freedom, honour, and ſafety, as his conceſſions may be effectuall; To paſſe the ambiguitie which may be concealed in theſe laſt words, and what conceſſions are meant, whither His Majeſties future conceſſions or thoſe already granted, we doe not thinke this delay ſafe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can we know how long it may be. Withall this clauſe gives ſome light to that part of your Lordſhips Declaration, For His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties comming with honour, freedome and ſafety, to ſome of his houſes in or neer <hi>London;</hi> This honour, freedome and ſafety being conceived by your Lordſhips to be ſuch as may inable His Majeſty to effectuate his conceſſions concerning Religion, appeareth to us to bee no leſſe, then a reſtoring of His Majeſtie to the exerciſe of his royall power, without ſecurity firſt had from him for ſettling Religion.</p>
               <p>The ſecond part of your Lordſhips anſwer, we humbly conceive doth rather confirme then ſatisfie our juſt complaint concerning re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions taken by your Lordſhips in matters of Religion, without the adviſe and conſent of the Kirke. For when your Lordſhips ſay that what is now Declared by the Parliament in order to Religion, is not upon any new grounds, but in purſuance of the ſame grounds contained in the Covenant and in the acts of the Generall Aſſembly yea, that in your Lordſhps demand concerning Religion, our adviſe was deſired; All this addeth to our juſt grievance, intimating to us, that your Lordſhips interpret the Covenant and acts of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly, otherwiſe then we do; forwe cannot conceive how your Lo: Declarat agreeth with the grounds of the Covenant, &amp; acts of the General Aſſembly but that it goeth upon new grounds, not contained in them. It is true, our adviſe was deſired in that demand concerning Religion, but it was alſo true that the demand was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon by your Lordſhips before our adviſe was deſired, and that the anſwer and adviſe returned from us hath not found good accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:124652:17"/>neither have your Lordſhips proceeded according to the ſame. And whereas your Lordſhips ſay, that as you have never hitherto taken any reſolutions in that which concernes Religion, without advice from the Kirke (and here give inſtance in thoſe particulars complained of by us) ſo you ſhall never doe any thing that may prejudice this juſt intereſt and liberty of the Kirke of <hi>Scotland:</hi> As we ſhall not call to minde all that is paſt, ſo that which is here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by your Lordſhips, doth yet further adde unto our grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, for to parallel and proportion the meaſure which wee may expect for the future, with that which we have in theſe late paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges received from your Lordſhips, cannot but leave us under juſt feares and ſad apprehenſions.</p>
               <p>The third part of your Lordſhips anſwer is in reference to our deſire of being ſatisfied upon the whole matter; where your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips againe referre us to the Declaration, as containing the grounds and reſolutions of the Parliament on the whole matter. This wee are not able to reconcile with that paſſage in the Declaration where your Lordſhips profeſſe, <hi>That you are reſolved not to ingage in any War before the neceſſity and lawfulneſſe thereof be cleared, ſo as all who are well affected may be ſatisfied therewith, and that reparation to ſuch breaches or injuries as are or ſhall be condeſcended on, ſhall be demanded in ſuch a juſt and fit way as ſhall be found moſt lawfull and expedient.</hi> The one paſſage hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth forth to us ſatisfaction on the whole matter, the other holdeth us ſtill in ſuſpenſe till the neceſſity and lawfulneſſe of the Warre be cleared, and the way of demanding reparation reſolved upon; for that your Lordſhips are pleaſed to ſay in the end, that it is cleare by the Declaration, that there is nothing therein which doth croſſe the demands concerning Religion, or is inconſiſtent with the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity thereof; what reaſon we have to be of another judgement ſhall appeare to your Lordſhips in our paper, which we are to preſent to your Lordſhips concerning the Declaration, unto which we referre our ſelves concerning our ſenſe of other particulars in this buſineſſe not here expreſſed.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A. Ker</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <head>The humble Repreſentation of the Commiſſion of the Generall Aſſembly: To the Honourable Eſtates of Parliament, upon their Declaration lately com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to us. <hi>Edinburgh 28.</hi> April <hi>1648.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SEing your Lordſhips have been pleaſed in your Anſwer to us of the twenty of this Moneth to remit us to your Declaration to the Kingdome, for ſatisfaction to our eight deſires formerly preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:124652:18"/>to your Lordſhips, as likewiſe to our other deſire concerning ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications to be made to the King, as wel as to the Parliament of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> And ſeeing your Lordſhips in the ſame Paper anſwering our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be ſatisfied in the whole matter, were pleaſed again to remit us to the Declaration, as containing the grounds and reſolutions of the Parliament on the whole matter. We have therefore taken to our ſerious conſideration your Lordſhips Declaration, to look after ſatisfactory anſwers to theſe our deſires, and to be ſatisfied in the whole matter: But in ſtead thereof, our feares and diſ-ſatisfactions are not a little increaſed by your Lordſhips Declaration. We ſhall not ſearch into ſome particulars in matter of fact, mentioned in the narrative part, neither ſhall we be curious after the reaſon, why in ſo large a Declaration concerning publicke dangers, duties, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies. There is no expreſſion for preſervation of Monarchicall Government in his Majeſties Poſterity, as well as in his own perſon.</p>
               <p>To the Preface we ſhall onely ſay thus much, that we could have wiſhed your Lordſhips had been pleaſed to expreſſe your ſelves more plainly, who are thoſe obſtructers and traducers of your Lordſhips proceedings: thoſe deceivers and abuſers of the people, which your Lordſhips (we ſuppoſe) point at in reference to this Kingdome, the Declaration being intended for the Subjects of this Kingdome, whom your Lordſhips call the abuſed people; If your Lordſhips meaning be, that the People are abuſed by the lyes and calumnies of Malignants, how comes it that ſo much favour and forbearance is granted to ſuch men? If any other then the Malignant party in the Kingdome be meant, we ſhould be glad they were made known.</p>
               <p>In the firſt part of the narrative, concerning the neceſſity, occaſion, and conſequence of the conjunction of both Kingdomes, We cannot but take notice of that which your Lordſhips ſay of thoſe common enemies, by whoſe counſells and practiſes the compoſing of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in the beginning was hindered, and what evills this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome might have expected, if theſe counſels and advices which gave firſt life and motion to theſe diſſentions, ſhould have been ſtill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent, We deſire it may not be forgotten who were theſe common enemies, and whoſe counſell it was that did prevaile about his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty in the beginning of theſe troubles, and whether there ought not to be a jealous and watchfull eye over any ſuch, if even after their joyning in the Covenant they be found in a way of compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with known Malignants and in a way of oppoſition to ſuch as have been moſt active and zealous in the Cauſe from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:124652:18"/>
               <p>Your Lordſhips adde, that in purſuance of the Covenant, this Kingdome joyned in Armes with their Brethren of <hi>England,</hi> and did proſecute theſe ends, till their common enemies were ſubdued, and moſt of them brought to ſuch condigne puniſhment, as the reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Parliaments thought fit. We ſhall here paſſe your Lordſhips omitting of the Treaty between the Kingdomes, which may bee thought to have had a neer and immediate influence in reference to the conjunction of theſe Kingdomes in Armes, although the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was the chiefe foundation thereof: But whereas your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips ſeem to intimate that the cloud of Malignancy was then ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently diſſipated, or at leaſt, that the Covenant was ſufficiently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in bringing Delinquents to ſuch condigne puniſhment as the reſpective parliaments thought fit; We are ſorry that we have cauſe to remember what forbearance, yea, favour and friendſhip hath been granted to many ſuch: and we are ſo far from thinking the danger from theſe former common enemies paſt and gone, that wee ſtill ſee Malignancy upon the one hand, as Sectariſme upon the other ſpringing up like roots of bitterneſſe to trouble, yea, to defile many in theſe Kingdomes, theſe are the hornes which yet puſh <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> on both ſides, the Lord prepare ſuch Carpenters as may cut off both the one and the other.</p>
               <p>As for the breaches of Covenant which your Lordſhips inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the following part of your narrative, we wiſh your Lordſhips to remember a paſſage in the Declaration of the Generall Aſſembly, and how cautiouſly they ſpeake of the breach of Covenant in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> the words are theſe, <hi>We would not be underſtood as if we meant either to juſtifie this Nation, or to charge ſuch a ſin upon all in that Nation; We know the Covenant hath been in divers particulars broken by many in both Kingdomes; (The Lord pardon it, and accept a ſacrifice) and we do not doubt but there are many ſeven thouſands in England, who have not onely kept themſelves unſpotted, and retained their integrity in that buſineſſe, &amp;c.</hi> That the Covenant hath been fouly and ſhamefull broken by as many of the prevalent party of Sectaries and their adherents, as ever tooke the Covenant, is clear and undeniable, and by their means hath come the reſiſting and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of Reformation, connivance at Hereſie and Schiſme, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things contrary to the Covenant. But it can as little be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, that there are dangerous breaches of Covenant by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants, both at home and abroad; And your Lordſhips know, true zeale, againſt breach of Covenant ſhould ſtrike equally on both hands, beginning to reforme at home. Your Lordſhips ſay well,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:124652:19"/>that the not takers of the Covenant are by the joynt Declaration of both Kingdomes declared to be publicke enemies to Religion and Country, and are to be puniſhed as profeſſed Adverſaries and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants: but we wiſh your Lordſhips may not forget to apply that paſſage of the ſaid Declaration to thoſe who have not to this day taken the Covenant in <hi>England,</hi> and that therefore, they may bee lookt upon by your Lordſhips as common enemies, which ought to be ſuppreſſed and puniſhed.</p>
               <p>The laying aſide of the Covenant out of the new Propoſitions ſent to his Majeſty to the Iſle of <hi>Wight</hi> we utterly diſapprove, and are heartily ſorry for it; but we wiſh there had not beene ſome guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe of this ſame kinde at home, when it was carried in the Committee of Eſtates, that there ſhould be no mention of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant in the publicke deſires ſent up in Auguſt laſt to his Majeſty. And whereas your Lordſhips doe enumerate amongſt theſe breaches of Covenant, <hi>That they who ought to be brought to tryall and condigne puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for hindering the Reformation of Religion, dividing the King from his People, one of the Kingdomes from another, or making any faction or party among the People, contrary to the League and Covenant, have been protected and aſſiſted;</hi> We ſhall here onely deſire your Lordſhips to remember, that all this is true of Malignants, as well as of Sectaries: and for our part, (whatſoever liberty there be in the manner or circumſtances) we doe not doubt, but the thing it ſelfe is neceſſary, both by the Word of God, and Solemne Covenant, <hi>viz.</hi> That juſtice bee done, and condigne puniſhments inflicted on all hinderers of Reformation and Peace, and all who make factions, contrary to the Covenant, whether they be Sectaries or Malignants: But if it was ſufficient that the moſt part of the Malignants were brought to ſuch condigne puniſhment, as the reſpective Parliaments thought fit, which your Lordſhips gave us a touch of in the precedent part of your narrative, wee leave it to your Lordſhips conſideration, whether you doe not hereby furniſh ſuch a retortion to thoſe that favour the Sectaries in <hi>England,</hi> as that they may plead from that principle in your Lordſhips declaration, that the puniſhment of Sectaries is to be referred ſimply to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> as they thinke fit, and that your Lordſhips muſt allow them the ſame latitude of favour toward the Sectaries, as before you have allowed both to your ſelves and them, towards the Malignants. Your Lordſhips adde as another breach of Covenant, that in ſtead of a firme Union and Peace between the Kingdomes, a breach hath
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:124652:19"/>beene endeavoured, which cannot be denyed to be a breach of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and therefore a rocke to bee the more carefully avoyded; It is our griefe that there is alſo cauſe to complaine of the Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant party at home, as no leſſe guilty of endeavouring a breach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Kingdomes.</p>
               <p>The attempts, injuries, and violences of that party of Sectaries againſt his Majeſties Royall Perſon, and the hard condition he is reduced unto by their meanes, we are very ſenſible of: And, as we have often before profeſſed, our prayers and endeavours accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our place and calling, have not beene, neither ſhall be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for the preſervation of his Majeſties Perſon and authority, in the preſervation of the true Religion, and liberties of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes: And we leave it to be pondered by your Lordſhips, whether they that obſtruct and hinder the requiring of ſatisfaction and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from his Majeſty, in point of Religion, before his reſtitution to the exerciſe of his Royall Power, do not upon the matter, and by conſequence obſtruct and hinder his Majeſties deliverance and reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, whereof ſuch ſecurity and aſſurance had from his Majeſty, might be a powerfull and effectuall meanes.</p>
               <p>As wee know not whom your Lordſhips meane when you ſpeake of ſuch, as had warrant from the Parliament of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for acceſſe to his Majeſty, and yet were debarred, and as no violence nor injury offered to a publicke Miniſter of another King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome can be excuſed; ſo we are informed, that the Souldiers Act in removing once the Earle of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> from <hi>Wooburne,</hi> was not onely diſclaimed, but his Lordſhip often thereafter permitted free acceſſe to his Majeſty.</p>
               <p>Your Lordſhips inſiſt upon three inſtances of the breach of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, one of the large Treaty, and two other breaches of the Treaty, 1643. As to the firſt, (which for orders ſake we begin at) We cannot ſay that it hold forth any convincing clearneſſe to us; Yea ſo far as we underſtand, the thing whereunto the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> was bound by the Treaty, was not inſiſted upon by the Commiſſioners of this Kingdome at <hi>London,</hi> but an alternative, for aſſiſtance againſt the Rebells by Forces or Monies: After which the Parliament of this Kingdome made a deſire of aſſiſtance by monies, which the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> promiſed to take into their conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; And ſeeing your Lordſhips in this ſame Declaration wave breaches of Treaty, in Money-matters, even where the Money was due by Treaty, We hope your Lordſhips will find it the more inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:124652:20"/>to inſiſt upon the not obtaining of that aſſiſtance by monies againſt the rebels, being a way not provided by the Treaty.</p>
               <p>Concerning the other two breaches which pitch upon the Treaty 1643. Firſt, your Lordſhips ſay, that according to the firſt article of that Treaty, the Covenant ſhould have been taken by both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, but that now by the prevalent party of Sectaries and their adherents, it is not only laid aſide in the new Propoſitions, and no execution of publick orders for taking it throughout the Country, but many in places of truſt have never taken it, neither are urged to take it. Certainly ſuch ſlieghting of the Covenant is a great ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and a high contempt of the Covenant; And it is very fit that this Kingdome ſhould deſire the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> to preſſe it, not onely upon perſons of truſt, but univerſally on all the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of that Kingdome; yet we are not convinced of any juſt ground of War againſt that Kingdome, in that which hath been inſtanced by your Lordſhips, eſpecially conſidering that the Covenant was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Repreſentatives, and other chiefe corporations in, <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> whereupon both the Generall Aſſembly, and the Parliament of this Kingdom have frequently mentioned in their Acts, Letters, and Declarations, the Union and conjunction of both Kingdomes by Solemne Covenant: neither are we without hopes, if things be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on in a fair and right way, that the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> may be brought a further length in the performance of this duty; Whereof we are the more confident, becauſe of the famous and frequent teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies given to the Covenant, and againſt the errours of the time, by the Miniſtry in divers Provinces in <hi>England.</hi> As for the laſt breach, which your Lordſhips conceive to be againſt the eighth Article of the ſame Treaty, 1643. We heartily wiſh, that the joint way of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications to the King by both Kingdomes once begun, had been continued, and do conceive very much prejudice to the Cauſe by the divided way: onely, we offer it to your Lordſhips further conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration whether this breach be not at leaſt diſputable, there being no mention at all in that Article of Propoſalls, Propoſitions, or Bills, but only of Ceſſation, Pacification, and agreement for Peace; ſo that it may juſtly be doubted whether the ſending of thoſe Propoſalls and Bils to the King without the conſent of this Kingdome, hath in it that certainty and clearneſſe of a breach of Treaty between the Kingdomes, as may be a ground of War: And if it be a breach of the Treaty for either Kingdome ſingly and dividedly to ſend Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions to his Majeſty, We ſhall crave leave that we may deſire to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:124652:20"/>to in formed, how this conſiſteth with that latitude which your lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips leave afterwards in this ſame Declaration in the manner of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Bills or Acts of Parliament to the King, for your Lordſhips deſire aſſurance of his Majeſtie to agree to ſuch Acts or Bills <hi>as ſhall be preſented unto him by his Parliaments of both or either Kingdoms, reſpecitivè.</hi> We might alſo inſiſt upon ſome Papers and Propoſitions preſented to his Maj. from this Kingdom at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> and much more upon the Pacification concluded there, with his Majeſtie, in reference to the disbanding and removing of the Rebels in this Kingdome, and that in a ſingle way (as we conceive) without the knowledge, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But we ſhall come to that which your Lordſhips make the reſult upon all theſe breaches of Covenant and Treaties, <hi>viz.</hi> That they call upon your Lordſhips to a duty to GOD, your King and Country, and to your oppreſſed Brethren in <hi>England,</hi> which your Lordſhips ſpeake more plainly in the next Clauſe, giving us to underſtand, that thoſe differences or breaches are ſuch, as if not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired by amicable indeavours, may otherwiſe neceſſitate this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to ingage in a warre, but that firſt your Lordſhips intend to ſend the three deſires (next mentioned in the Declaration) to the Parliament of <hi>England:</hi> And this is all the ſatisfaction we find to our ſecond deſire, which was, <hi>That according to the Treaties it may bee condeſcended upon, and Declared by the Parliament, what are thoſe brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Peace, which they take to bee a ground of Warre, and that reparation thereof may bee ſought.</hi> But as wee ſee no breach of Peace inſtanced in the Declaration, and as the three breaches of Treaties inſiſted upon by your Lordſhips, ſeeme to bee at leaſt debatable; So wee heare nothing of any reſolution of parliament, that ſuch breaches as are, or ſhall be condeſcended upon by your Lordſhips, ſhall be made known and ſent to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> as we expected, and they have deſired, by their Commiſſioners here; Onely we hear of three deſires to be ſent to the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> for Religion, His Majeſtie, and the Good and Peace of theſe Kingdomes: Wee conceive its the beſt and moſt juſtificable way of proceeding, that publicke, as well as private injuries be declared and made knowne to thoſe whom it concerneth to give ſatisfaction therein. Beſides all this, we fear your Lordſhips will hardly avoid a Nationall quarrell againſt the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> if the three inſtances before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned be inſiſted upon as breaches of Treaty to infer a War; becauſe when the Houſes were moſt free, and when there was no ſuch over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:124652:21"/>influence of the Sectaries party, even then they did not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the Iriſhes in this Kingdome, they did not enforce the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant on all their Officers, much leſſe on all Engliſh Subjects, neither would they then admit that they were oblieged by Treaty, not to ſend Propoſitions of Bills to the King, without the concurrence of this Kingdome.</p>
               <p>In all this that we have ſaid, it is far from our meaning to aſſume any judgement of the Treaties betweene the Kingdomes; Only becauſe your Lordſhips have remitted us to the Declaration, for ſatisfaction to our conſciences, as in other particulars, ſo in this of the breaches, We have humbly repreſented to your Lordſhips, wherein we are not clear and ſatisfied in our conſciences, to conſent and concur for our part upon ſuch grounds. And withall, ſeeing it is not only our deſire as Meſſengers of peace, but your Lordſhips profeſſed reſolution in this Declaration, that you will aſſay all Brotherly and amicable ways for repairing differences and making up breaches, We recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to your Lordſhips ſerious thoughts, whether it will not be moſt agreeable to that Brotherly way of proceeding between two Kingdomes in Covenant together, to deſire a Treaty with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>England,</hi> concerning the breaches and demands mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this your Declaration, Eſpecially ſeeing the way of Treaty was the way thought fit to be uſed in the years 1639. and 1640. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Kingdomes were joyned in Covenant; How much more now, being ſo conjoyned, are all poſſible and lawfull wayes to bee tried, for preventing the effuſion of more blood.</p>
               <p>In your Lordſhips firſt demand which concerneth Religion, there are ſome things wherewith wee cannot in our conſciences bee ſatisfied, as namely, 1. Becauſe the firſt two particulars, therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, <hi>viz.</hi> concerning the taking of the Covenant, and practiſing of the Directory of Worſhip, are preſſed only upon Subjects, which may be interpreted as tending to exempt the Kings Majeſty, not only from taking the Covenant, (which yet was laudably deſired in the Propoſitions of both Kingd.) but from having the Directory of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip practiſed in his family, which was a liberty that his Majeſty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to himſelfe in his late Conceſſions ſent to us, and in diverſe meſſages before ſent to the Houſes of Parliament at <hi>Weſtm.</hi> 2. We find nothing in this demand of any application to be made at, or about the ſame time to the King for obtaining aſſurance from his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty for his Royall conſent; But of this we have expreſſed our ſelves more fully in anſwer to your Lordſhips Paper of the twentieth
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:124652:21"/>of this moneth. 3. Althogh this is the ſecond time your Lordſhips cite in this Declaration a paſſage of the joynt Declaration of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, by which all that would not take the Covenant were declared to be publick enemies to their Religion and Countrey, and that they are to be cenſured and puniſhed as profeſſed Adverſaries and Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants; yet we find no ſuch thing declared or reſolved by your Lordſhips in this Declaration, in reference to thoſe who have not to this day taken the Covenant, as that you will hold them all for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Adverſaries and Malignants. We hope your Lordſhips will not think it juſt nor equall to preſſe ſuch a rule upon the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> except your Lordſhips be pleaſed to walk according to that rule your ſelves. 4. Your Lordſhips do ſimply and abſolutely deſire, that the Confeſſion of Faith tranſmitted from the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to the Houſes, be approven; whereas the Act of the laſt General Aſſembly, approving that Confeſſion of Faith hath in it ſome neceſſary cautions, proviſoes, and explanations; which as the Generall Aſſembly judged neceſſary to be added in their Act, ſo we do not think that part of your Lordſhips demand as it ſtands without any ſuch caution to be ſafe enough: which among other things ſhewes the danger and inconvenience of your Lordſhips ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king reſolutions in things concerning Religion without our advice and conſent. 5. As we deſire that Reformation of, and Uniformity in Religion, may be endeavoured by your Lordſhips in all fair, law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and brotherly wayes according to the Covenant, and heartily approve any ſuch deſire as your Lordſhips ſhall ſend to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England,</hi> by the advice and conſent of this Kirk, for in joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Covenant, and for bringing the Churches of CHRIST in the three Kingdoms to the neareſt Conjunction and Uniformity in one Confeſſion of Faith; Directory of Worſhip, and Presbyteriall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; So we would be very cautious, and tender when ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires are turned into cauſes of War, if not obtained, which is the preſent caſe, as we underſtand by your Lordſhips expreſſion in the precedent Paragraph.</p>
               <p>Your Lordſhips ſecond demand is, <hi>That the Kings Majeſty may come to ſome of his Houſes in or near</hi> London, <hi>with Honour, Freedome, and Safety, that applications may he made to him by Parliaments of both Kingdoms for attaining his Royall aſſent to ſuch deſires as ſhall be by them preſented to him for eſtabliſhing Religion as is above expreſt, and ſetling a well-grounded Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:124652:22"/>
               <p>This demand we conceive to be of dangerous conſequence to Religion and the Covenant for the reaſons and conſiderations fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, which we humbly offer to be conſidered by your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, 1. All applications and deſires to his Majeſty for Religion are ſuſpended till he come with Honour, Fredome and ſafty to ſome of his Houſes, in, or neere <hi>London;</hi> We know not what length of time this may draw to, or how much danger there may be in the delay 2. The eſtabliſhing of Religion here mentioned, as that which your Lordſhips intend to deſire of his Majeſtie, is according to that which is above expreſſed, where we doubt not your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips referre to your firſt demand which went before; Whereas the eſtabliſhing of Religion in ſuch a manner as is there expreſſed, we do not think ſafe, for the reaſons before given. 3. We conceive that this ſecond demand amounts to no leſſe then the reſtitution of his Majeſty to the exerciſe of his Royall Power before Applications made, and deſires preſented to him, much more before aſſurance and ſecurity had from him, for the ſetling of Religion in the right man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and according to the Covenant. For beſides what we have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in our laſt Paper preſented to your Lordſhips that this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, freedom, and ſafety is conceived by your Lordſhips to be ſuch, as may enable his Majeſty to effectuat his Conceſſions concerning Religion; And what is that leſſe then the exerciſe of his Royall power reſtored? This we further adde, that we humbly conceive, his Majeſties Honour may comprehend, or may be made uſe of as comprehending, not only the poſſeſſion of his Revenews, but alſo the exerciſe of his Royall Government; Next, being in freedome, he may repare to any part of his Dominions in <hi>Scotland, England</hi> or <hi>Ireland;</hi> And laſtly, being reſtored to be in a condition of ſafety, he may provide Forces for guarding Himſelfe againſt all apprehended dangers, for if Guards ſhould be ſet about him, by his Parliament, it will be ſaid to be contrary to the condition of freedome; So that bring reſtored to ſome of his Houſes, in, or near <hi>London,</hi> with Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Freedome, and Safety, We do not conceive what he ſhall want of the exerciſe of his Royall Power Conſidering withall, that neither himſelfe, nor any others will conceive the Honour, Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Safety to be Kingly, and ſuch as becomes his Royall Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, if he ſhall want the exerciſe of his Royall Power: Yet this reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of his Majeſty to the exerciſe of his Royall Power, before ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity had from him for ſettling Religion, Your Lordſhips know by our eight Deſires, and other wayes, is conceived by us to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:124652:22"/>with the ſafety and ſecurity of Religion. 4. If his Majeſty were once come with Honour, Freedom and Safety to ſome of his Houſes, in, or neare London, We know not what influences he may have upon the Houſes of Parliament to obſtruct and hinder their preſenting of Bils to Him, for enjoyning the Covenant, aboliſhing Prelacy, and the Booke of Common-prayer, Eſtabliſhing the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith, Directory of Worſhip, and Presbyteriall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Or what ſtrength his Majeſty ſo reſtored may again attain by the aſſiſtance of the Popiſh, Prelaticall, and Malignant party, for a new and bloody Warre, to the devaſtation of theſe Kingdomes, and the ruine of our Religion and Liberties. Which things we have the more cauſe to feare and apprehend, his Majeſty having declared and profeſſed, that he is obliged in conſcience to emprove all the power which God ſhall put in his hands, for the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Epiſcopacy. 5. To inſiſt upon the bringing of his Majeſty to ſome of his Houſes, in, or neer London, before ſatisfaction and ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty had from him in point of Religion, and in ſuch other things as are neceſſary for the ſafety of the Kingdoms, could not as we conceive but be an exceeding great diſcouragement and offence to the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians in <hi>England,</hi> who will conceive (if ſuch a thing be preſſed upon them) that the remedy propounded in your demand is worſe then the diſeaſe. And we have alſo heard, that the Parl. of <hi>England,</hi> when they were as free as ever they were, would never agree to his Majeſties comming to <hi>London,</hi> with honour, freedome, and ſafety, without ſecurity firſt had from him in ſuch things as are neceſſary for Religion, and the ſafety of the Kingdome. 6. Seeing your Lordſhips are oblieged by the third Article of the Covenant, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his Majeſties Perſon and Authority, in the perſervation and defence of the true Religion, and Liberties of the Kingdome; We conceive your Lordſhips ſhould not demand from, nor preſſe upon the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> His Majeſties reſtitution with Honour, Freedom, and Safety, except with that qualification in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and with a ſubordination to Religion and the Liberties of the Kingdoms, And how can this ſubordination according to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant be ſaid to be obſerved in your Lordſh. demand as it ſtands; for, if His Majeſty be brought to ſome of His Houſes, inor near <hi>London,</hi> with Honour, Freedome, and Safety, before ſo much as applications be made to Him for eſtabliſhing Religion and Peace, we then leave it to your Lordſhips conſciences, whether His Majeſty ſhall not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:124652:23"/>to His Honour, before Jeſus Chriſt be reſtored to his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and ſet upon his Throne of Government in His Church: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther His Majeſty ſhall not be in a condition of Libertie before the Ordinances of Chriſt have a free courſe, and whether His Majeſties ſafety ſhall not be provided for and ſecured; before either Church, or Kingdome can ſay they are in a condition of ſafety. And is this to endeavour the ſettling of Religion before all worldly intereſts, or rather to make it come after the Kings intereſt? 7. We fear that if after ſo many inſtructions from the Parliament. Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Committee of Eſtates to their Commiſſioners at <hi>London,</hi> from time to time, for endeavouring in the firſt place the ſettlement of Religion, and then to endeavour the removing of the Civill dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, and the reſtitution of the King, upon his firſt giving ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in Religion and the grounds of a ſolid Peace; And if after it was declared by this Kingdome, (during His Majeſties being at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi>) that they could not admit of his Majeſties coming to <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in freedome, unleſſe his Majeſty granted the Propoſition concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Covenant and Religion, and gave a ſatisfactory Anſwer to the reſt of the Propoſitions; Likewiſe, if after ſuch a Declaration of the Parliament of this Kingdom, <hi>January</hi> 16, 1647, for his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties being in ſome of his Houſes, with ſuch attendance as the two Houſes ſhould think fit, untill He give ſatisfaction in the Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; If after all this it be now inſiſted upon, that his Majeſty may be reſtored with Honour, Freedome, and Safety, before ſuch ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had from Him, we feare it ſhall lie as a great ſcandall upon this Kingdome, and as too ſenſible and apparent a change of their former principles and profeſſions in a point ſo much concerning the ſecurity of Religion. 8. We are very apprehenſive, that your Lordſhips urging the diſpoſal of the Kings Perſon in <hi>England,</hi> in ſuch a way as that he may come to <hi>London</hi> with Honour, Freedom, and Safety, without his Majeſties giving or your Lordſhips deſiring his Majeſty to give ſatisfaction and ſecurity in Religion, &amp; in ſuch things as belong to the ſafety of the Kingdome (without which there can be no laſting ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity expected to Religion.) At it is a farre different point from the urging of a joynt intereſt in the diſpoſing of the Kings Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon by both Kingdomes for the good of both, ſo it will be fudged by moſt of all parties in <hi>England,</hi> that ever concurred in this Cauſe, to be ſo prejudiciall to their Nationall Rights and Liberties, and ſuch an enchroachment thereupon (though your Lordſhips declare
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:124652:23"/>you have no ſuch intention) as that it will unite them all in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to this Kingdome, and conſequently alienate them from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Uniformity in Religion, according to the Covenant. As theſe reaſons make us conceive your Lordſhips ſecond demand to import no ſmall danger to Religion, So we would not be underſtood as if we had any thoughts to decline the reſtoring of his Majeſty to the ſame condition he was in, by the agreement of both Kingdomes. when he was taken away by a party of the Army under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> that both Kingdomes may freely make their applications to him.</p>
               <p>Concerning your Lordſhips third demand, That the preſent Army of Sectaries may be disbanded, for the ends expreſſed in the demand, As we think no perſons what ſoever fit to be imployed or entruſted in the Armies of either Kingdom, who have not taken the Covenant, and that all Sectaries in <hi>England</hi> that are in Arms ſhould be disban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and diſarmed, So we conceive there is alſo reaſon for your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips to foreſee and provide againſt the danger of the riſing again of the Popiſh Prelatical and Malignant party in armes, and therther, becauſe of the late commotions begun by ſome of them both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> There being alſo ſome both in <hi>Wales</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> actually in arms, who have diſcovered and declared their principles and ends to be very Malignant; wherein we are informed they are the more animated and encouraged upon confidence of ſome agreement between his Majeſty and this Kingdome. It is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be conſidered, that this Demand being joyned with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, the preſent Army in <hi>England</hi> disbanded, and his Majeſty brought to <hi>London</hi> with Honour, Freedome and Safety, how eaſily may all the Malignant, Popiſh and Prelaticall party in his Majeſties Dominions flock unto him? Which how prejudiciall it may be, his Majeſty keeping ſtill his principles, is eaſie to be judged.</p>
               <p>As for the exceptions added in your Lordſhips demand, to paſſe the ambiguity thereof, your Lordſhips except from the laid disband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Garriſons neceſſary to be kept in <hi>England,</hi> and deſire that theſe Garriſons may be commanded by ſuch as have or ſhall take the Covenant, and are well-affected to Religion and Government, but do not deſire any ſuch thing concerning the Gariſons themſelves; which may be underſtood as a tacite confeſſion on your part, that all the Gariſons to be kept in <hi>England</hi> may be of ſuch as have not taken nor ſhall take the Covenant, nor are well affected to Religion and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:124652:24"/>Government, provided that thoſe Gariſons be commanded by ſuch as your Lordſhips deſcribe.</p>
               <p>We have but one point more to adde, concerning this third and laſt demand: For we cannot conceal our feares and apprehenſions, that your preſent reſolutions and proceedings, and the entertainment of Engliſh Souldiers, whereof many are Papiſts and Malignants, and ſome eminent in Malignancie, is not the way to further, but to retard and hinder the disbanding of the preſent Army in <hi>England,</hi> and to fruſtrate the ends your Lordſhips propoſe in your Declaration for the disbanding of that Army.</p>
               <p>And whereas your Lordſhips declare, that it is not your intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at all, to make a Nationall engagement againſt the Parliament and Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> but for them; as we ſhall not preſume to ſpeak of the Nationall Rights and Priviledges of another King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, So we cannot ſee how the principles of your Lordſhips Declaration can conſiſt with the firſt part of our third Deſire, which was, That there may be no ſuch quarrell or ground of the Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re as may break the Vnion between the Kingdomes; for we conceive there are diverſe ſuch quarrels in the Declaration as fall directly and neceſſarly upon the votes and proceedings of the Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, even when they were moſt free.</p>
               <p>Concerning that which your Lordſhips adde in reference to the latter part of our third deſire, and to out whole fourth deſire, We humbly conceive, it is very farre ſhort of that which is no leſſe your Lordſhips duty then our deſire; for, 1. Your Lordſhips onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare Aſſociation and Conjunction of Forces with thoſe who ſhall refuſe to ſweare and ſubſcribe the Covenant, which doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude Aſſociation of Forces with ſuch as neither have taken, nor ſhall take the Covenant, ſo that they be not urged thereto, and ſo not nerckoned among refuſers. This we have the more reaſon to take notice of, becauſe your Lordſhips have before in this ſame De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration complained that there is no urging of the Covenant in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> nor no execution of publike Orders for taking of the ſame. Which being ſo; how ſhall your Lordſhips finde the Malignants in <hi>England</hi> to be refuſers of the Covenant, except your Lordſhips en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force it upon them, which we ſuppoſe your Lordſhips intend not to do? 2. Your Lordſhips do not declare, that if any who have not taken, and ſhall not take the Covenant, nay not ſo much as they that ſhall refuſe the Covenant, if they riſe in Armes, your Lordſhips will
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:124652:24"/>oppoſe them, and endeavour to ſuppreſſe them, onely your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips ſay, you will not aſſociate nor joyn forces with them. 3. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as your Lordſhips ſay, <hi>That you will be ſo farre from joyning or aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating with the Popiſh Prelaticall, or Malignant party, if they ſhall again riſe in Armes, either to oppoſe or obſtruct all or any one of the ends of the Covenant, that you will oppoſe and endeavour to ſuppreſſe them as enemies to the Cauſe and Covenant;</hi> We beſeech your Lordſhips to conſider, whether this part of your Declaration doth not reſerve a latitude, that if the Popiſh, Prelaticall, or Malignant party ſhall riſe in Armes for the Kings reſtitution, and can but have ſo much cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (with is more nor probable) as to conceal their intentions of obſtructing or oppoſing all, or any one of the ends of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, in ſuch a caſe it may be free to your Lordſhips inſtead of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing or endeavouring to ſuppreſſe them, that you ſhall both pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect their perſons and eſtates, and alſo joyne or aſſociate Forces with them. In all which we have the more cauſe to be full of feares and apprehenſions, becauſe of ſo many Engliſh Malignants, even now protected and entertained in this Kingdome, in hopes of military imployments, yea diverſe of them (as we are informed) ſuch as have ſerved againſt this Cauſe and Covent.</p>
               <p>As to that which ſollowes relating to our ſeventh deſire, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſuch as are to be intruſted in Armies and Committees, we ſhall need to ſay no more then was expreſſed in our humble repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>March</hi> 29. Namely, that your Lordſhips omit in your Anſwer ſome of the qualifications expreſſed in our deſire, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as have given conſtant proofe of their integrity and faithfulneſſe in the Cauſe, and againſt whom there is no juſt cauſe of jealouſie, that ſo we may the more confidently encourage our Flocks to follow the Cauſe of God in their hands, and not to doubt of their fidelity; Which qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification being contained in our deſire, and omitted in your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Anſwer, we are not without feares, that this omiſſion may be made uſe of by ſome, as if your Lordſhips had not meant to agree ſully to that deſire, and ſo take occaſion to deale for employing and entruſting ſuch in the Committees and Armies, as may be juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excluded by the qualifications contained in our ſaid deſire.</p>
               <p>Theſe things having beene before preſented to your Lordſhips, and there being nothing in your Lordſhips Declaration to ſatisfie or take off theſe our feares, but ſuch expreſſions inſiſted upon as keepe aloof from the qualifications deſired by us, all that are unbyaſed, may
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:124652:25"/>eaſily judge whether we have not herein ſome reall ground to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied.</p>
               <p>That which followeth in the ſaid Declaration concerning the reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuing of his Majeſties Perſon, that He may come with Honour Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſafety to, or neer <hi>London</hi> where both Kingdomes may make their applications to him, for ſettling Religion and Peace, we have before ſpoken fully to it. And whereas your Lordſhips adde a kind of <hi>Salvò</hi> in ſatisfaction to our fifth and ſixth deſires, it will plainly appeare that theſe deſires are not ſatisfied by any thing here expreſſed in your Lordſhips Declaration. Your Lordſhips ſay, You reſolve not to put in His Majeſties Hands or in any others what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, any ſuch power whereby any of the ends of the Covenant may be obſtructed or oppoſed: But may it pleaſe your Lordſhips to give us leave to put your in minde, 1. That your Lordſhips words may be underſtood, either in this ſenſe, that you are not reſolved to put any ſuch power in His Majeſties Hands, And if ſo, your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips know; what you reſolve not now, you may reſolve afterwards; Or in this ſenſe, that your Lordſhips are reſolved that your ſhall put no ſuch power in His Majeſties Hands, and if ſo, then there remaines ſome doubt how far that power extends, which your Lordſhips con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſhall not be able to obſtruct or oppoſe any of the ends of the Covenant, or endanger Religion and Presbyteriall Government; Or whether it be meant to be extended to his Majeſties negative voice. 2. When your Lordſhips ſay, that you are not reſolved to put any ſuch power in His Majeſties Hands, this needeth not hinder your Lordſhips yeelding and acquieſcing if others put ſuch power in His Majeſties Hands; For reſolutions, not to doe a thing, may ſtand with reſolutions nor to hinder it. 3. When your Lordſhips have reſolved to oppoſe the puting of any ſuch power in his Majeſtis Hands, as may be deſtructive to Religion; Yet upon ſuppoſition, that His Ma jeſtie is come to <hi>London</hi> with Honour, Freedome and Safety, we doubt, whether it may not prove impoſſible to your Lordſhips to hinder the putting oft ſuch a power in His Majeſties Hands.</p>
               <p>Your Lordſhips adde what aſſurance you intend to crave from His Majeſty for ſatisfaction in point of Religion; But withall, we obſerve three limitations or qualifications joyned therewith, which (ſo far as we are able to judge) leave this great point in a very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous uncertainty. 1. Your Lordſhips reſolve, that his Majeſty
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:124652:25"/>give this aſſurancè for Religion, <hi>before any agreement or condition to be made with His Majeſty,</hi> which is the expreſſion choſen by your Lordſhips inſtead of that clauſe in our ſixt deſire, <hi>Before his reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the exerciſe of his Royall Power.</hi> If your Lordſhips expreſſion were only a more ſmooth one, with the like ſecurity to Religion, (ſuch as your Lordſhips Anſwer <hi>March</hi> 27. did put us in hopes of) we ſhould have chearefully acquieſced: but we are ſo far from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the like ſecurite to Religion that we rather feare your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips qualification may make void and firuſtrate the ſecurity that we deſired. For firſt, It clearely ſuppoſeth, that his Majeſty ſhall come with Honour Freedome, and ſafety to <hi>London,</hi> before any agreement or condition to be made with Him; For ſuch agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or condition to be made with his Majeſty being poſterior to the aſſurance to be had from Him for Religion, muſt be much more poſterior to his Majeſties coming to, or neer <hi>London</hi> with Honour, Freedome, and Safety according to the method of proceedings propoſed in the Declaration; Now being once at <hi>London,</hi> with Honour, Freedome, and Safety, and that without any agreement or condition made with Him, it is not probable to us, that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty will then deſire any agreement or condition, unleſſe it be for ſome Conceſſions on his Parliaments part, and among other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions probably ſomewhat for Epiſcopacy too, for eſtabliſhing whereof, He conceiveth Himſelfe obliged in conſcience to make uſe of His Power as was before obſerved. The reſult of this point that we humbly conceive is, that notwithſtanding of that clauſe, <hi>before any agreement or condition to be made with his Majeſty,</hi> or any thing elſe in the Declaration, His Majeſty may be reſtored to the exerciſe of His Royall Power before ſecurity had from Him for Religion as we deſired.</p>
               <p>The next qualification added by your Lordſhips, immediately is in theſe words, <hi>having found His late Conceſſions and offers concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Religion not ſatisfactory;</hi> where firſt, the words <hi>having found,</hi> may be variouſly underſtood, either, <hi>when His Majeſty ſhall have found,</hi> or, <hi>when your Lordſhips ſhall have found,</hi> or, <hi>becauſe His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty hath found,</hi> or <hi>becauſe your Lordſhips have found.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next, the words, <hi>not ſatisfactory,</hi> are as doubtfull, and may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted in ſeverall ſenſe, either that His Majeſties late Conceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Offers concerning Religion, <hi>are not ſatisfactory in themſelves,</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:124652:26"/>or, <hi>that they are neither ſatisfactory to your Lordſhips nor to us,</hi> or the meaning may be only, <hi>that they are not ſatisfactory to us.</hi> Which doubtfulneſſe in the ſenſe of the words we have more cauſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, becauſe your Lordſhips have not hitherto returned us any clear or poſitive anſwer to our fifth deſire; <hi>That his Majeſties late Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions and Offers concerning Religion, as they have been by the Church ſo may be by the Parliament declared unſatisfactory;</hi> Only your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, are pleaſed here to make a light tranſition over that which we conceived to be unto us a grave Subject of a Solemne De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration.</p>
               <p>The third qualification in the aſſurance to be required from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, is, that he ſhall agree to ſuch act or acts of Parliament, and Bils, as ſhall be preſented unto Him by His Parliaments of both or either Kingdomes reſpectively for enjoyning the Covenant, and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Presbyteriall Government, Directory of Worſhip and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith in all his Majeſties Dominions. But we humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, it were more for the Glory of God, good of Religion and his Majeſties own happineſſe, that his Majeſty ſhould after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Godly reforming Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> and of the beſt Chriſtian Emperours of old in the Chriſtian Church, Declare his own zeal and forwardneſſe for the Reformation and ſettling Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and that your Lordſhips ſhould do well to ſollicite and incite his Majeſty hereunto, rather then to ſeem to yeeld ſo farre as that his Majeſty ſhall be free for his part, till his Parliaments of both or either Kingdomes reſpectively agree what acts or Bills to preſent to him; The preparing and preſenting whereof, how much it may be retarded and obſtructed by the prevalency both of Malignants and Sectaries, we know not: ſeeing therefore His Majeſty oweth a duty doth to God and to his people for the Reformation and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of Religion, your Lordſhips may do better to ſollicite his Majeſty, and to deſire that he will poſitively declare himſelf willing and ready for his part and for that duty which is incumbent to his Majeſty, and that he give aſſurance for the ſame in the particulars. Your Lordſhips further declare in reference to our eighth and laſt deſire, <hi>that you are willing to ſubjoyn to the grounds of your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking an Oath, wherein both in the framing thereof and otherwiſe your Lordſhips are willing the Church ſhall have their due intereſt as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly in the like caſes.</hi> Where, as we know not how far your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips meaning doth reach in the word <hi>other wayes,</hi> and in the word
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:124652:26"/>
                  <hi>due;</hi> ſo we know not why your Lordſhips did not think fit to agree to our deſire as it was conceived, and the words ſtood, <hi>viz, that there may be no ingagement without a ſolemn Oath, wherein the Kirk may have the ſame intereſt which they had in the Solemn League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant;</hi> which deſire is ſo far unſatisfied, that for our intereſt in the matter of the Oath, and in the grounds of the undertaking, we do nat ſee it allowed or preſerxed to us, but rather that the Declaration holdeth forth the grounds of the undertaking already reſolved upon by your Lordſhips; only leaving us an intereſt in the forme of an Oath to be ſubjoyned, and that not without ſome uncertain and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious qualifications, as hath been touched. Mean while we ſee only a Declaration without an Oath; and as Declarations are alterable by Parliaments, and their proceedings ſometimes not agreeable to their Declarations (which he experience of theſe times hath taught us) ſo if there were an Oath ſubjoined to the grounds of undertaking expreſſed in this Declaration, we could not account it a lawfull Oath, but that it would make the buſineſſe worſe.</p>
               <p>Your Lordſhips adde ſomewhat further, relating to the matter of our firſt and ſecond deſires, namely, <hi>that your Lordſhips are reſolved not to engage in any War before the neceſſity and lawfulneſſe thereof be cleared, ſo as all who are well affected may be ſatisfied therewith, and that reparation to ſuch bpeaches and injurics as are or ſhall be conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended upon, ſhalbe demanded in ſuch a juſt ane fit way, as ſhalbe found moſt lawfull and expedient.</hi> This clauſe, as likewiſe that which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that many of the dangers with the grounds and reſolutions, are by this Declaration of your Lordſhips made known to this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſeems to hold us in ſuſpence, till all the dangers, grounds and reſolutions be made known, and till the lawfulneſſe and neceſſity of the War be cleared, and the way of ſeeking reparation reſolved upon; yet eour Lordſhips may be pleaſed to remember, that in that part of your Anſwer to us of the twentieth, which is a return to our deſire of knowing fully your Lordſhips reſolutions, and being ſatisfied on the whole matter, we were remitted to the Declaretion, as contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the grounds and reſolutions of the Parliament on the whole matter.</p>
               <p>As to that which followeth, concerning a preſent putting of the Countrey in a poſture of defence as in <hi>Anno</hi> 1643. we ſhould be glad it were made to appear really that the grounds principles and end were the ſame now, they were in the year 1643. Otherwiſe the like
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:124652:27"/>Act upon different grounds, and for different ends make it not the ſame cauſe. Your Lordſhips do indeed ſpeak of the principles ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Declaration, as the ſame with the firſt principles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in our Nationall Covenant, and in the Solemn League and Covenant. But what reaſon we have to conceive they are new and different principles, may appear by the ſeverall particulars before mentioned. We cannot here paſſe a new interpretation which the Declaration puts upon the Solemn League and Covenant, <hi>viz. That we did ſolemnly ſweare and promiſe before God and his Angeli to endeavour Reformation of, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity in Religion and Church-Government in all his Majeſties Dominions according to the Word of GOD, and the example of the beſt Reformed Churches.</hi> Where we paſſe your Lordſhips limiting and reſtricting of Uniformity more then the Covenant doth: which may infer that Uniformity in Church-Government between the Churches of CHRIST in theſe three Covenanted Kingdoms, is not to be urged in any other man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or meaſure then we have a precedent of in other reformed Kirks; but that which here we chiefly aim at, is the following clauſe of the Declaration, <hi>viz. And not only to the utmoſt of our power, with our m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an, and lives to ſtand to the defence of our dread Soveraign, his perſon and Authority, in the preſe vation of the true Religion and Liberties of the Kingdoms, but alſo in every cauſe which may concern His Majeſties Honour, to concur according to the Lawes of this Kingdom, and duty of good ſubjects.</hi> Yet your Lordſhips know that no ſuch interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation bath beene made by the Aſſemblies of the Kirk of the Solemn League and Covenant, as your Lordſhips are pleaſed here to make of it: If it be ſaid, that your Lordſhips meaning was only of our Nationall Covenant, yet it may be obſerved withall that the plain and grammaticall conſtruction of the words will carry that interpretation either upon the Solemn League and Covenant only, or both upon it and upon our Nationall Covenant How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, although our National Covenant only were here fixed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, concerning which there is ſuch an expreſſion in the ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Generall Aſſembly, <hi>Anno</hi> 1639. to his Majeſties com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner and the Lords of Secret Councell, yet there are ſome weighty conſiderations which we humbly offer againſt the applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that Supplication of the Aſſembly, to the preſent duſineſſe; for, 1. His Majeſty was at that time giving ſatisfaction to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick deſires of this Kirk concerning Religion; We heartily wiſh
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:124652:27"/>we might ſay the like now. 2. We do not ſee the Cauſe ſtated in the Declaration to be for his Majeſties honour, and ſo to fall within that duty expreſſed in the Declaration of the Generall Aſſembly. And as one of the ends of the Covenant was his Majeſties honour and happineſſe, and your Lordſhips alſo have acknowledged in your Oath of Parliament, that the honour, happineſſe, and greatneſſe of the Kings Majeſty, doth depend on the purity of Religion as it is now eſtabliſhed in this Kingdome, So whatſoever croſſeth or preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diceth the grounds of the Covenant, or any of the ends thereof, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not with us finde any ſuch commendation as to be a cauſe which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth his Majeſties honour. 3. Whatſoever we owe to the King in civill matters diſtinct from the Cauſe of Religion, ſure all theſe other duties are with a ſubordination to the glory of God, and good of Religion; and we are very confident it was and will be far from the thoughts of the Generall Aſſembly, under colour of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Honour to concur with him, or any in his Name, in a cauſe which is hurtfull and prejudiciall to the good of Religion, and to the other ends of the Solemn League and Covenant; yet the cauſe ſtated in the Declaration, we humbly conceive to be ſuch. 4. It may be remembred that the <hi>Croſſe-petition</hi> having cited the ſame clauſe of the ſaid Petition of the Generall Aſſembly, and making uſe thereof in order to an engagement in War in his Majeſties quarrell againſt the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> was declared againſt by the Commiſſion of the Generall Aſſembly, <hi>Anno</hi> 1643. And among other particulars it was then declared, that the limitations expreſly mentioned in the words cited out of the Aſſemblies Supplication, <hi>viz. according to the Lawes of this Kingdom, and duty of good Subjects,</hi> were interpreted by ſome that ſpake at the time in the generall Aſſembly, to be all one as if it had been ſaid, <hi>within this Kingdome,</hi> we not knowing of any Lawes of this Kingdome of further extent. It was alſo then obſerved any may now be applied and remembred, that the Nationall Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant having been ſubſcribed in the Yeares 1581. and 1590. before King <hi>James</hi> was King of <hi>England,</hi> and being qualified in the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Heads and Articles by expreſſe limitations and reſtrictions to this Kirk and Kingdome, to the Religion, Laws and Liberties of <hi>Scotland,</hi> can no more be extended to municipall debates, and to the Laws and Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> unto which we are ſtrangers, then the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> can judge of our Lawes, and determine our differences, the two Kingdoms being ſtill independent each on other, and not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:124652:28"/>one to another, as the firſt Article of the large Treaty fully declareth.</p>
               <p>As to that we find in the cloſe of the Declaration, that this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Scotland</hi> will now make it evident, as they have often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that their quietneſſe, ſtability, and happineſse doth depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſafety of the Kings Majeſties Perſon and maintenance of his greatneſse and Royall authority, who is Gods Vicegerent ſet over us for maintenance of Religion and miniſtration of Iuſtice; we ſhall only put your Sordſhips in mind, that your National Covenant join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with his Majeſties Safety, his good behaviour in his Office, and ſaith, <hi>That the quietneſſe and ſtability of our Religion and Kick doth depend upon the ſaety, and good behaviour of his Maieſty, as upon a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Inſtrument of Gods mercy granted to this Countrey for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of his Kirk, and miniſtration of Juſtice.</hi> Otherwiſe, if a King do not his duty for the Maintenance of the true Religion, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Iuſtice, it is ot his ſafety alone, that make his Peaple to be in quietneſse and happineſse; Withall, as our quietneſſe and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe dependeth on his Majeſty, and his doing of his duty as an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Miniſter of God for good, So the Honour, Greatneſse, and Happineſse of the Kings Royall Majeſty, and the welfare of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, depend upon the purity of Religion, as is well expreſsed in your Lordſhips Oath gf Parliament.</p>
               <p>And now we ſhall with your Lordſhips favour and permiſſion make this concluſion upon the whole matter, That as we neither were nor are againſt an Engagement with this Kingdom in War, but have been and ſhall be willing to conſent thereto, if once ſatisfied in our conſciences concerning the clearneſſe, lawfulneſſe, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the Cauſe and quarrell, and concerning our calling, manner of proceeding, Inſtruments to be entruſted, ſecurity to be had for Religion, and other particulars contained in our former Papers not yet ſatisfied by your Lordſhips. So we are neceſſitate to profeſſe and declare to your Lordſhips, that we cannot, we dare not in our conſciences agree to an Engagement upon ſuch grounds, and in ſuch a way as is ſtated in your Lordſhips Declaration; And therefore for our exoneration do diſſent from the whole complex buſineſſe in the ſaid Declaration, as not containing clear and convincing grounds of undertaking of a Warre, nor providing for the ſecurity of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, nor clearly diſclaiming his Majeſties late Conceſſion and offers as unſatisfactory, nor tending to the ſuppreſſion of the Malignant
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:124652:28"/>party, but rather to compliance with them, as we humbly conceive, nor preſerving the Liberties and known intereſt of the Kirk, nor propoſing the way of Treaties, and all other wayes of Peace to be ſought and aſſayed before a Warre. For which reaſons, and others before mentioned, upon the particular heads of the Declaration, we plainly declare our diſſent from the complex circumſtantiat ſtate of the preſent buſineſſe contained in the ſaid Declaration, and take to witneſſe, God, Angels, and men, that your Lordſhips have not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed warning from the Watchmen, And that we ſhall be free of all the diſtractions, confuſions, miſeries and blood, which may follow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Lordſhips proceeding to an engagement in Warre, upon the grounds of the Declaration. We further call to record, the ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of all hearts, and the righteous Judge of all the world, that our not concurring proceedeth not from want of zeal againſt Sectaries, nor from any remiſſeneſſe in that which may concern his Majeſties true Honour and Happineſſe, and the preſervation of Monarchicall Government in him and his Poſterity, nor from any want of tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Priviledges of Parliament, nor from any want of ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie with our afflicted and oppreſſed Brethren in <hi>England,</hi> In refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to all which our proceedings have been and ſhall be (we truſt) reall teſtimonies of our affection and ſincerity; But our not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring proceedeth meerly from tenderneſſe in the point of ſecurity of Religion, and union between the Kingdoms, and from the unſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factorineſſe of the grounds of your Lordſhips Declaration, as hath been expreſſed in the particulars. Wherefore we humbly beſeech your Lordſhips to interpret favourably and charitably any liberty which we have uſed (the matter being ſuch as lyeth ſad and weighty upon our Conſciences) and that your Lordſhips would alſo be pleaſed to be mindfull of making good that paſſage of your Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where you ſay <hi>that you are reſolved not to engage in any War, before the neceſſity and lawfulneſſe thereof be cleared, ſo as all who are well-affected may be ſatisfied therewith;</hi> Which if your Lordſhips ſhall be pleaſed to do, there is a door of Hope yet open, and we ſhall not ceaſe to pray unto the Lord (as he ſhall aſſiſt us) that a Spirit of counſell and underſtanding and of the fear of the Lord may be upon you, and tha God would graciouſly rid both your Lordſhips and us out of all hid and lurking ſhares, and ſo guide your Lordſhips, as that there may be yet a ſweet and harmonious joining of hearts and hands upon right Principles, Grounds and motives, in a right way, and for the right ends.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:124652:29"/>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Edinb.</hi> 
                     <date>6. <hi>Iunii,</hi> 1648.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <head>The humble Vindication of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of the Generall Aſſembly, and their late Proceedings: <hi>In Anſwer to the LETTER of the High and Honourable Court of PARLIAMENT, Dated</hi> May 11. <hi>to the ſeverall Presbyteries in the Kingdom.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALthough we doubt not but the particular Presbyteries will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently return anſwer to the Parliaments Letter ſo far as concerneth them, (wherein divers Presbyteries have already given example to the reſt) yet the chief purpoſes of that Letter reflecting all along upon our late proceedings, and the Letter being alſo prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and publiſhed for common view and uſe; The great truſt put upon us will not allow us to be ſilent in ſuch a caſe. And the greater cauſe we have to vindicate our proceedings in this manner, becauſe whileſt we had juſt reaſon to expect from the Parliament a clear and reall ſatisfaction to our deſires, ſeconded by ſo many Provinciall Synods, in ſtead of ſuch ſatisfaction, that Letter came abroad with many reflections upon our proceedings, neither was any thing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of communicat or made known from their Lordſhips to us, that we might have been heard for clearing our own actions before the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulging and ſpreading abroad of the Letter.</p>
               <p>To the Preface of the Letter we anſwer, that as it is too manifeſt how many and great ſcandals are thrown upon us and our proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings by the favourers of Malignants and haters of Reformation and Presbyteriall Government; So we know not either among our ſelves, or in any Aſſemblies of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> and favourers of Sectaries, or haters of the Perſon of the King and of Monarchicall Government, who throw ſcendals upon the Parliaments actions; And if any ſhall by ſufficient proof diſcover any ſuch in this Kingdom, it will quickly appear how far the Aſſemblies of this Church (and we for our part) ſhalbe from conniving at, or beating with them; yea the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:124652:29"/>Generall Aſſembly and Commiſſioners have already declared ſo much, and ſo often both for the preſervation of the Monarchicall Government in his Majeſty and his poſterity, and againſt Sectaries. And there hath been alſo ſo long and reall proofe both of the loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty of this Reformed Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> to his Majeſties Father, and to himſelfe, and of zeale in executing Church Diſcipline againſt Sectaries (wherever any were found) that the world may bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with our Conſciences of our integrity both in the one and in the other, although we ſhould altogether hold our peace. Error will ſooner comply with errour then truth can, and favourers of Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants have been and may againe turne to be favourers of Sectaries, to ſerve their turne and ſave their intereſt for the time. For our part as we did before ſo we doe ſtill, clearly and ingeniouſly profeſſe that we looke upon Sectaries and Malignants as enemies to be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, as rocks to be avoided on the right and left hands.</p>
               <p>We ſee no cauſe why the ſeverall Presbyteries need to be conjured as they will anſwer to the great God not to ſuffer themſelves to be poſſeſt with unjuſt and undeſerved prejudices againſt the Parliament and their proceedings: The fear of God, &amp; conſcience of their duty, wil keep them upon the one hand from unjuſt and undeſerved preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices againſt their Lordſhips and their proceedings, and upon the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand from obeying unjuſt Decrees, and complying with iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty although eſtabliſhed by a Law.</p>
               <p>What their Lordſhips profeſſe concerning their preferring of no earthly thing to their duties for Religion, and concerning their reall endeavours to ſatisfie the moſt tender conſciences, by their Lordſhips great complyance with our many deſires: All this wee leave to the ſearcher of the hearts, and tryer of the reynes, who can and will judge thereof: This we can ſay for our ſelves, that to this day, we have not received a ſatisfactory Anſwer from their Lordſhips unto any one of our deſires preſented to their Lordſhips for the ſafety and ſecurity of Religion, but under colour of yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſomewhat, our deſires were more dangerouſly refuſed, then if they had been flatly rejected.</p>
               <p>If that which followeth in the Letter hold good, viz. <hi>That it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be by any with truth and juſtice alleadged that their Lordſhips have in the leaſt meaſure wronged, or violated the true Priviledges and Liberties of the Church,</hi> we are greatly to be blamed and cenſured for complaining in one of our Papers to the Parliament, that their Lordſhips have
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:124652:30"/>very much prejudiced the true priviledges and liberties of this Kirks, and for proteſting (upon that occaſion) againſt ſuch prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratives, and for preſervation of the liberties of the Kirke in time comming. But now how much truth and juſtice wee had for the ground of our grievance and proteſtation, all who will not ſhut their eyes againſt the cleare light may eaſily underſtand. For was it ever before heard or knowne, that any Parliament of this Kingdome did without the knowledge and conſent of thoſe who had for the time, the truſt of the publicke affaires of the Kirk, determine, judge, and declare, by an antecedent judgement, matters ſo highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Religion, as theſe contained in the Parliaments late De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration. Wherein there are not onely dangerous expreſſions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Confeſſion of Faith, Directory of Worſhip, and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriall Government(as we have particularly inſtanced in our late Declaration) but likewiſe in the cloſe a ſtrange and new ſenſe put upon the Covenant and Acts of Generall Aſſemblies, without ſo much as firſt conſulting us concerning ſuch a ſenſe thereof, which might have beene prevented if they had conſulted us therein: Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding of all which, the Declaration being communicate to us from the High and Honourable Court of Parliament, and wee having promiſed a ſpeedy returne thereto, which accordingly after eight dayes we performed, (the matter being copious) the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was ordered by the Parliament to be Printed, and the three de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands contained therein ſent away to <hi>England,</hi> with out ſtaying a little for cur Anſwer (which we had let them know we were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring) whereas a very ſhort delay might have by the bleſſing of God brought unto their Lordſhips more light, and matter of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thoughts.</p>
               <p>We can as eaſily acquit our ſelves of any incroachments upon the unqueſtionable Rights of Parliament. We are obliged by Solemne Covenant to endeavour the preſervation of the Rights and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parliament; And to encroach upon the ſame were indeed a hainous crime, wherewith if any ſhall reproach us, let them take heed what the ninth Command will exact of them; yet they who will remember how in all ages, the moſt faithfull ſervants of God have uſually been traduced as troublers of, and encroachers upon the Rights of the Civill Magiſtrate, will not much marvell that what hath been, is now.</p>
               <p>As to the three inſtances mentioned in the Letter, to prove
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:124652:30"/>that great encroachments are made upon their Lordſhips unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable Rights. Firſt, it is ſaid, <hi>What can be more civill then to determine what Civill duties we ought to pay to our King, or what Civill powers hee ought to be poſſeſſed of?</hi> We aske again, whether in our late conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with their Lordſhips concerning an engagement in War, there was any thing more proper to be inſiſted upon by us, then the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Religion before all worldly intereſts, and particularly, that ſecurity may be had from his Majeſty for the point of Religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his reſtitution to the exerciſe of his Royall power? Muſt not duties to God (whereof the ſecuring of Religion is a maine one) have the ſupream and firſt place, duties to the King a ſubordinate and ſecond place? Next as we have not determined what Civill duties the Parliament ought to pay to the King, or what Civill powers he ought to be poſſeſſed of; and as it is competent to the Parliament to judge of Civill duties between the King and his People, in their owne way; ſo can we not admit that it is proper and competent onely to them to judge of thoſe duties; for the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſecond Table as well as of the firſt, as namely, the duties between King and Subject, Parents and children, Husbands and Wives, Maſters and ſervants, and the like, being contained in, and to be taught and cleared from the Word of God, are in that reſpect, and ſo far as concerneth the point of conſcience a ſubject of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall Doctrine, and in difficult caſes a ſubject of cognizance, and judgement to the Aſſemblies of the Kirke. And here it is not to bee paſſed that the Kirke of <hi>Scotland</hi> in the large Confeſſion of Faith, ratified by Acts of Parliament, did long ſince determine the duties of the King and Subjects: The like whereof may be ſeen in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Confeſſions of Faith of the Reformed Churches.</p>
               <p>Secondly, whereas it is ſaid, <hi>Is there any other Authority in this Kingdom but that of the Parliament, and what flows from them, that can pretend Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative power in the choice of the Inſtrument and Managers of their publik Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions?</hi> We humbly ask, is there any Eccleſiaſtical Authority within this Kingdom that hath pretended or doth pretend to ſuch a power? for we know no ſuch thing. An Authoritative power and choice of the Inſtruments to be entruſted in Committees of Parliament &amp; Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, doth not belong unto us, but unto the Parliament. Nevertheles it was very competent for us among other things requiſite for the ſafety and ſecurity of Rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gion and our Solemne Covenant, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent to the Parliament the Qualifications which we judged from
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:124652:31"/>Gods word to be neceſſary in ſuch as are entruſted with the mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of ſo great Affaires, and ſo highly concerning our Religion and Conſciences; Which we have had the more reaſon to inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for our owne and others ſatisfaction, we being deſired to joyne and concur in the buſineſſe. Suppoſe a Miniſter preaching before the Election of Magiſtrates (which is uſuall) and ſhewing from the Word of God the Qualifications requiſite in Magiſtrates, and that none ought to be choſen but ſuch as are ſo and ſo qualified; who will challenge ſuch a Miniſter of aſſuming the Authoritative power of chooſing Magiſtrates? And if the chooſing of particular Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in Cities and Boroughs contrary to the Rules and Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Word, be ſinfull and blame-worthy, how much more the committing of ſo great a publicke truſt in Committees and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to divers not qualified with the neceſſary Qualifications.</p>
               <p>To the third Inſtance, which asketh, <hi>Is it a ſubject for the Diſpute of Church Judicatories, whether his Majeſty hath a negative voice in Parliament, or not?</hi> We anſwer, ſo far as the Scriptures of the Old or New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament hold forth any light to us, what Power is due, and what is not due to Kings, it well agreeth with our places and callings, to communicate ſuch light to others as we ſee need. Wee know no Church Judicatory that hath diſputed whether his Majeſty hath a negative voice in Parliament; but we had juſt reaſon to ſupplicate the Parliament that they might not intereſt themſelves in any quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell for his Majeſties Negative voyce, becauſe of the great dangers which may thereby come to Religion, not onely by future diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments of the ſo much deſired ſettlement of Church affaires, but by quarrelling the Solemne League and Covenant it ſelfe, and the begun Reformation and Uniformity in Religion which hath been purchaſed with ſo much pains, hazards, loſſes and ſufferings.</p>
               <p>And now we ſhall take all theſe three inſtances joyntly, and make this further anſwer to them all. Firſt, although the points had been meerly Civill, yet by the Confeſſion of Faith agreed upon by the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminster</hi> and approved by the Generall Aſſembly of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> as ſound and Orthodox as the Act more particularly beareth, we are allowed to apply our ſelves to the Parliament by way of humble ſupplication even in Civill matters, The Parliament alſo having in their Declaration expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their deſires and reſolutions, that the ſaid Confeſſion of Faith be confirmed and eſtabliſhed, have upon the matter allowed us to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:124652:31"/>their Lordſhips concerning ſuch things. Next we ſay, that in all the three inſtances which are given, our ſupplications and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires were to avert what we juſtly conceived to be deſtructive to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: We hope no man will have the face to ſay that the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of the Church may ſupplicate againſt dangers of Religion which fall within the firſt Table, but not againſt dangers of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which fall within the ſecond Table, or that they may ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate againſt dangers of Religion ariſing from other men, but not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt dangers of Religion in which his Majeſty is any way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, or which flow from a bad choice of the Inſtruments and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagers of publicke reſolutions.</p>
               <p>The Epiſcopall diſeaſe of medling with Civill affaires we truſt through Gods mercy, neither hath, nor ſhall have any place among the Miniſtry of this Kingdome, who by their Nationall Covenant abjured the Civill places and power of Kirk-men. Onely we ſhall deſire it may be remembred that there were other Epiſcopall diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and diſtempers beſide this, as namely, encroaching upon the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and priviledges of Eccleſiaſticall Aſſemblies, the forcing of the conſciences of Gods people, and perſecuting ſuch who could not in conſcience obey. Wherefore it is neceſſary that all the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall evills and diſorders be carefully avoided. And as we doe not doubt the enſuing Generall Aſſembly will doe what ſhall be fit for them to prevent the villifying and contemning the authority of Parliament, if it be found in danger to be villified, ſo we humbly conceive they will not be unmindfull to prevent the villifying and contemning of the authority of their owne Commiſſioners.</p>
               <p>The following clauſe in the Letter putteth over to the Generall Aſſembly any of the Miniſtery, <hi>who ſhall offer to ſtir up the Subjects of this Kingdome to diſobey or deny to give Civill obedience to their Lawes, it being expreſly provided by the ſecond and third Acts of King</hi> James 6. <hi>his</hi> 8. <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in</hi> Anno 1584. <hi>that none of his Majeſties Subjects under the paine of Treaſon impugne the Authority of Parliament.</hi> Where firſt we ſhall deſire that two knowne diſtinctions, which in this paſſage of the Letter ſeem either to be confounded or forgotten, may be remembred. Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill obedience to Acts of Parliament is either in things unlawfull and contrary to the Word of God, or in things lawfull and right. In the former caſe it is a ſin to obey: in the latter caſe, a ſin not to obey. Againe the Authority of Parliament is one thing, an Act of Parliament another thing; We doe ſtill acknowledge their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:124652:32"/>when we obey not this or that Act. And whatſoever bee the Treaſon of impugning the Authority of Parliament, it can be no Treaſon to obey God Father then man: Neither did the Generall Aſſembly of <hi>Glaſgow</hi> 1638. and ſuch as were active for the Covenant at that time commit any Treaſon when they impugned Epiſcopacy and <hi>Perth</hi> Articles, although ratified and ſtrengthened by Acts of Parliament and ſtanding Laws then unrepealed.</p>
               <p>As to the two Acts cited in the Letter, if the Order of the Printed Acts be followed, the third hath nothing in it of what it is cited for, neither know we for what uſe it can be cited and applyed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept to the abridging of the Liberties of Eccleſiaſticall Aſſemblies; for it diſchargeth all Judicatories and Judgements, Conventions and Aſſemblies Eccleſiaſticall, without his Majeſties ſpeciall licence and Commandement, which how contrary it is to the word of God, to the example of the primitive Church, to the Judgement of found Divines, to the Liberties of this Kirke, and to our Solemne Covenants, is more manifeſt then to need that we ſhould inſiſt upon it. But if the Order of the unprinted Acts be followed, the ſecond of theſe Acts doth not mention the Authority of Parliament, but of his Majeſty and his Councell: However we are heartily ſorry for the citation of the acts of that Parliament, a Parliament which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>introduced Epiſcopacy, and ſo made defection from the Nationall Covenant ſworne three yeares before: For Captaine <hi>James Stewart</hi> then Earle of <hi>Arran</hi> and Chancellour, and the few Prelates of that time contrived and procured ſuch Acts of Parliament as might ſerve their ends. The ſame Acts were alleadged and urged by his Majeſties Commiſſioner in <hi>Anno</hi> 1638. for Epiſcopacy, whereunto this Anſwer was made at that time, <hi>The Acts of Parliament,</hi> 1584. <hi>are of ſeverall natures but they were proteſted againſt by the Miniſters of</hi> Edinburgh <hi>in the name of the Kirke of</hi> Scotland <hi>at the Market Croſſe of</hi> Edinburgh <hi>when they were proclaimed, and as they were made in that time which was called the houre of darkneſſe of this Kirke Tyranized over by the Earle of</hi> Arran, <hi>ſo are they repealed,</hi> 1542. <hi>Cap.</hi> 114. It is not to be forgotten, That after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of thoſe Acts of Parlament, they were ſo generally diſliked by al good men, that the chief Courtiers of that time thought it neceſſary to employ Maſter <hi>Patrick Adamſon,</hi> a chiefe deviſer of theſe Acts to make a Declaration of the meaning thereof in his Majeſties Name, which he accordingly performed. Concerning which Declaration the ſaid Maſter <hi>Patrick</hi> pretended Archbiſhop of St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:124652:32"/>in his renunciation make this Confeſſion. <hi>As where I am bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened to be the ſetter forth of a Booke called the Kings Declaration wherein the whole Order of the Kirke is condemned and traduced; I proteſt before God, that ſo I was commanded to write the ſame by the Chancellour for the time, but chiefly by the Secretary, another great Courtier who himſelfe penned the ſecond Act of Parliament, concerning the Power and Authority of Judicatory to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute in the Kings Power, and that it ſhould not be lawfull for any Subject to reclaime from the ſame, under the penalty of the Act which I ſuppoſe was Treaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſide that Declaration his Majeſty himſelfe having received a ſupplication from divers well-affected Miniſters with their Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſions upon the ſaid Acts of Parliament, did pen with his owne hand another Declaration of the meaning thereof: But by both thoſe Declarations it may be eaſily underſtood, that the ſaid Acts were intended for innovating and changing the Government and Diſcipline of this Kirke, for ſetting up Biſhops, and for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the beſt Miniſters, and accordingly they were made uſe of afterwards for the ground of a charge againſt the Miniſters that were baniſhed.</p>
               <p>It ſhall not be amiſſe here to inſert that part of the Miniſters A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimadverſions (given in to his Majeſty at that time) which concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ſecond Act of that Parliament; the words are theſe, <hi>As concerning the ſecond Act, the Narration thereof, appeareth to bee ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous againſt ſome of the Miniſtery, which wee would wiſh to be reformed or otherwiſe conceived, except the truth thereof were verified. And as to the ſubſtance of the Act it ſelfe, it attributeth to your Majeſty a Sovereigne power of Judgement not onely upon the perſons of your Subjects, but alſo in all matters wherein they or any of them ſhall be apprehended, ſummoned, or charged, &amp;c. Which appeareth to be very ſtrange, the like whereof we beare not to have been practiſed in any Chriſtian Commonwealth, and cannot ſtand with the Word of God, for although the perſons of men are ſubject to your Majeſty and Civill Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges when they offend againſt your Lawes, yet matters Eccleſiaſticall and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning conſcience, no Chriſtian Prince can juſtly claime, nor ever claimed to himſelfe ſuch power to judge, Seeing the Prince in this behalf is a member of the Kirke, and Jeſus Chriſt onely the head, who onely hath power to give Laws in matters of Conſcience; and ſo ſaid the godly Ambroſe,</hi> Imperator bonus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Eccleſiam non ſupra Eccleſiam eſt: <hi>And to confound the Jurisdiction, Civill and Eccleſiaſticall, is that thing wherein men of all good Judgements have juſtly found foult with, in the Pope of Rome, which claimeth to himſelfe the power of both the ſwords, which is as great a fault to a Civill Magiſtrate to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:124652:33"/>claim and uſurp, and eſpecially to judge upon Doctrine, Errors and Hereſies, he not being placed in Eccleſiaſticall function to interpret the Scriptures, the warrants hereof out of the word of God we are likewiſe to bring forth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereunto we ſhall adde a paſſage out of the recantation of Mr. <hi>Patricke Adamſon</hi> ſubſcribed with his hand before famous witneſſes and exhibit to the Synod of <hi>Fyffe.</hi> the paſſage is this. <hi>There are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in that ſecond Act of Parliament divers others falſe intentions for to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame the Miniſtrie and to bring the Kirke of God in hatred and envy with their Prince and Nobility, burdening and accuſing the Miniſters falſly of Sedition, and other crimes, whereof they were innocent (as likewiſe it is written in the ſame Act and Declaration thereof that Soveraign and Supream power pertaineth to the King in matters Eccleſiaſtical, which is worthy to be condemned not to be contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among Chriſtian Acts, where the power of the word is to be extolled above all the power of Princes, and to be brought under ſubjection to the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The words of the ſecond Printed Act cited, or the third unprinted (ſo Farre as concerneth the purpoſe of the Letter) we find to be thus: <hi>That none of his Lieges nor Subjects preſume or take upon band to impugne the dignity and the Authority of the ſaid three Eſtates, or to ſeeke or procure the innovation or diminution of the Power and Authority of the ſame three eſtates or any of them in time comming under the paine of Treaſon,</hi> Theſe words we humbly conceive as they relate to the conſtitution of Parliament made of the three Eſtates and to the Authority thereof, being in that manner conſtituted, not to the obedience of their particular Acts, ſo if they be urged and preſſed according to the meaning and intention of the Act before declared, they will conclude under Treaſon all who impugne the Power and Authority of Biſhops, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bots and Pryors as the third Eſtate of Parliament.</p>
               <p>To the concluſion of the Letter wee ſhall need to ſay but little, having already in other papers expreſſed our ſelves fully, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the unſatisfactorines of their Lordſhips Declaration, and the unlawfulneſſe of the preſent engagement; Which although it bee pretended to be the ſame cauſe for which this Kingdome hath don and ſuffered ſo much, yet if it be remembred that the Kirks deſires for the point of Religion are not granted, that the wel-affected who were moſt zealous in the cauſe from the beginning are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally againſt this engagement, that it is carried on, by ſuch as wer for the moſt part diſ-affected to the Cauſe in the beginning, and were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the former expeditions; that the Publick affaires are intruſted into many new hands, ſuch as we cannot be confident of; Theſe and the like conſiderations will quickly make it appear that the cauſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:124652:33"/>is not the ſame, but hugely different from what it was, and that the ſame grounds and principles which made us Active in further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the former expeditions, hinder us from furthering this.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Edinb. <date>
                        <hi>10.</hi> Junii <hi>1648.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <head>The Humble Advice and Petition of the Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, To the Honourable Eſtates of Parliament.</head>
               <p>WHile wee were about preparing of our thoughts concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the unſatisfactorineſſe of a paper communicated unto us from your Lordſhips upon <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> being a draught of an Anſwer from the Parliament ot the ſeverall Petitions of Presbyteries, Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods and Shires tendered to them: There was a motion made unto us from your Lordſhips by the Lord Ley and the Lord of <hi>Armſtoun,</hi> to wave a particular return unto that Paper, ſeeing it was not to be looked upon as the ſenſe or mind of the Parliament, in reſpect that before the Parliament had taken it into debate or conſideration, they did think fit to communicate it to this Commiſſion; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to deſire that the Commiſſioners would be pleaſed to tender un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Parliament their adviſe, concerning the ſecurity of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in anſwer to the ſeverall Petitions preſented to the Parliament of late from Synods, Presbyteries and Shires: Unto which motion we make this humble returne.</p>
               <p>For the firſt part of the motion; We are reſolved to lay aſide the conſideration of that Paper, and to make no Repreſentation of our thoughts thereupon, if your Lordſhips be pleaſed to make no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uſe thereof.</p>
               <p>As for the other part of the motion, calling for our adviſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning an Anſwer to the Petitions preſented from ſeverall Shires, Presbyteries and Synods unto the Parliament: Although we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conceive, your Honours may clearly perceive what is our judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by our Papers preſented to your Lordſhips from time to time; yet being required we ſhall againe faithfully and freely tender this our humble adviſe.</p>
               <p>Wee call to record the ſearcher of all hearts, the Judge of the world, that our not concurring with your Lordſhips proceedings hitherto, hath not flowed from want of zeal againſt Sectaries, for the ſuppreſſion of whom, and for the advancement of the work of Reformation, we are ready to hazzard all in a lawfull way; Nor from any remiſſeneſſe in that which concernes his Majeſties true Honour and happineſſe, and the preſervation of Monarchical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:124652:34"/>in him and his poſterity, nor from any want of tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the priviledges of Parliament; nor from want of Simpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie with our afflicted and oppreſſed Brethren in <hi>England;</hi> nor from partiall or ſiniſtrous reſpect to any party or perſon whatſoever within the Kingdome; But from meen tenderneſſe in point of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Religion, and the Union between the Kingdoms, and from the unſatisfactorineſſe of the grounds of your Lordſhips Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as hath beene expreſſed more at lengthen our Repreſentation: Notwithſtanding your Lordſhips, to our very great griefe, have proceeded to a Levie, whereby heavy burdens and preſſures have been laid upon many faithfull Covenanters, moſt forward in all former expeditions, and averſe from this, onely for want of ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction concerning the neceſſity and lawfullneſſe thereof, promiſed in your Lordſhips late Declaration, but not as yet performed.</p>
               <p>It is therefore our humble advice that the above-mentioned Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being ſo juſt in themſelves, and flowing from the grounds aforeſaid, as they ought in equity to have been granted, ſo they ought yet to be granted by the ſecuring of Religion, ſtaying the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Levy; and according to our former deſires by eſſaying Treaties with <hi>England,</hi> applications to His Majeſty, and all other faire and amicable wayes for removing the differences betweene the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, before ſending any forces to <hi>England</hi> or any other way of engagement in War. And leaſt the taking of <hi>Barwicke</hi> and <hi>Carliſle</hi> which is ſo ſcandalous to this Nation) bee looked upon by <hi>England</hi> as a breach of Union on your part; That your Lordſhips would be pleaſed to make it appeare, that neither the Parliament, or any of your number have had any acceſſion to the ſurpriſall or ſupplying of theſe Townes, nor ſhall we have any correſpondence or comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with thoſe who have been actors therein.</p>
               <p>We doe alſo conceive it neceſſary for ſatisfaction of the Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, That his Majeſties late Conceſſions and offers concerning Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion may by your Lordſhips directly and poſitively be declared unſatisfactory to this preſent Parliament.</p>
               <p>That although we would not be underſtood, as if we have had, or have, any thoughts of declining the reſtoring of his Majeſty to the ſame condition Hee was in, by the agreement of both Kingdomes when he was taken away by a party of the Army under Sir <hi>T. Fairfax,</hi> that both Kingdoms, may freely make their Applications to him; yet your Lordſhips would be pleaſed to Declare, That there ſhall be no engagement for reſtoring his Majeſty to one of his houſes with
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:124652:34"/>Honour freedome and ſafety (which doth amount to no leſſe then the reſtitution of his Majeſty to the exerciſe of his Royal power, for the reaſons holden forth in our late Repreſentation never yet anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) before ſecurity and aſſurance be had from his Majeſty by his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Oath under his hand and ſeal, That he ſhall for himſelf and his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, conſent and agree to Acts of Parliament, injoyning the League and Covenant, and fully eſtabliſhing Presbyterian Government, Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Worſhip, and confeſſion of Faith in all his Majeſties Dominions; and that his Majeſty ſhall never make oppoſition to any of theſe, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour any change thereof.</p>
               <p>That your Lordſhips wil make it appear that you mean to be far from intereſting your ſelves in any quarrell for his Maj. that may put into his Majeſties hands ſuch power, as may not only bring the by-gon proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of both Kingd. in the League and Covenant in queſtion, but alſo for the time to come make void all the authority of Parl. though proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing never ſo rightly in reference to Religion and Liberties of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes.</p>
               <p>That a clear and direct courſe be laid down and declared not only not to aſſociate nor joyn in Councels or Forces with the Popiſh, Prelaticall or Malignant party, but alſo to oppoſe and effectually indeavour to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe all ſuch of them as have already riſen or ſhal hereafter riſe in Arms upon whatſoever pretence, as enemies to the Cauſe and Covenant on the one hand; as well as Sectaries on the other.</p>
               <p>That nothing be don in carrying on the engagement, which may break the union of the Kingdomes, or may diſcourage or diſ-obliege the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian party in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe it is our grief, and the grief of all the well-affected, that thoſe who have been of conſtant and approved integrity in the Cauſe and have been very inſtrumentall under God for our deliverance, ſhould be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for want of ſatisfaction to their conſciences to leave the ſervice; and that others who have not given conſtant proofe of their integrity and faithfullneſſe, and againſt whom there is juſt cauſe of exception and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, ſo that we cannot exhort our flocks to be confident of their fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; yea, and divers that have been in reall oppoſition to the Cauſe, are entruſted with the managing of your Lordſhips publik reſolutions: That therefore your Lordſhips will be pleaſed in your wiſdome to provide a timous remedy herein That there be no Engagement, without a Solemn Oath, wherein the Kirk may have the ſame intereſt which they had in the ſolemn League and Covenant the Cauſe being the ſame.</p>
               <p>As we doe humbly inſiſt with your Lordſhips for ſatisfaction to our
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:124652:35"/>former deſires expreſſed in our former papers, ſo it is our humble petition to your Lordſhips, That in ſuch things as have beene ordained by your Lordſhips, and put in execution by your Order, contrary to ſome of theſe deſires, ſome effectuall remedy may be found out by your Lordſhips wiſdome and goodneſſe for the helpe thereof; That all who ſince the beginning of this Levie, through tenderneſſe of conſcience, have ſuffered any wayes, may be repaired, all unuſuall and grievous courſes impoveriſhing good people and utterly diſabling them to ſubſiſt, may be hereafter avoided: and the intolerable inſolency, prophaneneſſe, blaſphemies, and manifold outrages that of late have appeared in the Souldiers, may be ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſhed and repreſſed; That no Ordinance nor Order may iſſue from your Lord hips in prejudice of the liberties of the Kirke, and of the free exerciſe of any part of the Miniſteriall calling, all which they have from Jeſus Chriſt the onely Head and Law-giver in his Kirke, and which your Lordſhips are obliged by ſolemne oath in our Covenants to maintaine: And that as it is our griefe, that whilſt your Lordſhips have been ſeeking our advice, you have been and are making grievous Acts, as we are informed ſo we deſire your Lordſhips in the feare of God to be wary of making or maintaining ſuch Acts and namely, That you put not the power of arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in the hands of any intruſted by your Lordſhips, nor or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine any Oaths to be impoſed or exacted, that may be ſnares to mens conſciences.</p>
               <p>All which we ſeriouſly recommend to your Lordſhips, as you deſire not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke againſt your ſelves and your poſterity the wrath of the moſt High God, and that the Lord ſhould not avenge the quarrell of a broken Covenant upon the Parliament and Kingdome of Scotland. But if your Lordſhip ſhall be pleaſed to hearken to our humble advice, and to ſatisfie the conſciences of the well-affected in the Kingdome to the worke of Reformation, by granting their juſt deſire; Your Honours ſhall be bleſſed of God, the Lord of the whole earth; the people of God ſhall bleſſe you in the name of the Lord, and bleſſe the Lord for you; You ſhall binde up the wounds of this diſtreſſed and diſtracted Kingdome, endear the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the well-affected, diſappoint the deſignes of the diſaffected, and your Names ſhall be a praiſe unto the preſent and ſucceeding generations: And wee ſhall powre out ſupplications before him, who ſitteth and judgeth among Gods, to endue your Lordſhips with the Spirit of counſell and of the feare of his Name; that your Reſolutions may be rightly ordered and tend to his glory, the ſecurity of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion the honour and happineſſe of the King and his poſterity, and the peace and ſafety of the Kingdomes.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A. KER.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
